<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Akeeba SocialMagick User's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Nicholas</firstname><othername>K.</othername><surname>Dionysopoulos</surname></personname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Akeeba Ltd</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <copyright>
      <year>2025</year>

      <holder>Akeeba Ltd</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled "The GNU Free
      Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <chapter xml:id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section xml:id="what-is-socialmagick">
      <title>What is Akeeba SocialMagick?</title>

      <para>Akeeba SocialMagick is an extension which automatically generates
      OpenGraph images for your site's pages, and populates their OpenGraph
      data. This allows for rich link previews when you share your content on
      social media sites, instant messaging applications, web chat services /
      applications and so on. Having an eye-catching image preview whenever
      you, or someone else, shares a link to your site increases the number of
      people who will click the link. On some platforms, such as Facebook,
      including an OpenGraph image is the only way to entice the algorithm to
      put the content sharing your link in front of people.</para>

      <para>All you need to do on your side is create templates which tell
      SocialMagick how to use any combination of a color background, the
      article / category images, and your item / page title to generate an
      OpenGraph image.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="requirements">
      <title>Server requirements</title>

      <para>The PHP and Joomla version requirements for SocialMagick can be
      found in our <link xlink:href="https://www.akeeba.com/compatiblity.html"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Compatibility
      page</link>.</para>

      <para>Beyond that, you need to have installed and enabled either the
      <code>imagick</code> or <code>gd</code> extension in PHP. If you are not
      sure if this is the case, please check out <link
      linkend="which-ext-is-installed">our instructions</link>. If you need to
      enable one of the two extensions, we strongly recommend the
      <code>imagick</code> extension which allows PHP to use the more powerful
      and flexible ImageMagick library for image manipulation. You can learn
      how to do so by reading <link linkend="enable-imagemagick">our
      instructions on enabling <code>imagick</code></link>.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>We strongly recommend using the <code>imagick</code> extension
        whenever you can. It renders colour much better, it is faster, and it
        supports SVG files.</para>

        <para>The <code>gd</code> extension is older, it does not render
        colour as well (the colours look either washed out or with too much
        contrast compared to what you see on your browser and the image source
        file), it is slower, and it does NOT support SVG files at all.</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="how-does-it-work">
      <title>How does it work</title>

      <para>SocialMagick's main reason of existence is to generate images
      which will be displayed along a page's title and description when you
      share a link to that page on social media (Facebook, Mastodon, X /
      Twitter, BlueSky, etc), instant messaging apps (Google Messages, Apple
      Messages, Whatsapp, Signal, Viber, etc), and other sites which allow
      rich link preview (e.g. Discord). The information about the page of your
      site is embedded into the HTML of your page using the <link
      xlink:href="https://www.opengraph.xyz/"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">OpenGraph standard</link>.
      For the sake of brevity, we call these generated images "OpenGraph
      images".</para>

      <para>SocialMagick generates OpenGraph images by combining one or more
      of a solid / semi-transparent colour card, an image of your choice, an
      image from your content (e.g. the intro, full article, or category
      image) or a static image, and text (content title, or static text) in a
      way defined by a <emphasis role="bold">Template</emphasis>. Whether to
      generate OpenGraph images and data, which template to use, and (some of
      the) template options can be overridden in the content itself, e.g. in
      articles and categories, or at the menu item level. This gives you
      excellent flexibility in determining which pages of your site should
      have OpenGraph data and images, and how they will look like.</para>

      <bridgehead>The extensions</bridgehead>

      <para>SocialMagick is a set of extensions consisting of a component, a
      system plugin, several plugins in the <code>socialmagick</code> group,
      and some secondary plugins.</para>

      <para>The component is used to manage the OpenGraph image Templates used
      by SocialMagick.</para>

      <para>The system plugin is the extension which does the real work:
      display the OpenGraph tab in edit forms, create the OpenGraph images
      when needed, and add the OpenGraph information into your HTML
      pages.</para>

      <para>The <code>socialmagick</code> plugins allow SocialMagick's system
      plugin to integrate with core and third party components. For example,
      the <guilabel>SocialMagick - Menus</guilabel> plugin allows SocialMagick
      to integrate with Joomla menu items. It is necessary to display the
      OpenGraph tab in menu items, and for SocialMagick to be able to override
      OpenGraph options with those explicitly set in the menu item.</para>

      <bridgehead>Options cascade</bridgehead>

      <para>The OpenGraph options in SocialMagick are designed to <emphasis
      role="bold">cascade</emphasis>. In other words, more specific places
      where you can set OpenGraph options override the settings set in less
      specific places.</para>

      <para>At the least specific place, we have the options you set in the
      component's <guilabel>Options</guilabel> page, and the options you set
      in each Template. These define the base set of options. Everything more
      specific than that will override them.</para>

      <para>At the next level we have <emphasis
      role="bold">Categories</emphasis>. A category can override the options
      from the base set, as well as the options set in its parent category.
      That is to say, if you have subcategories then the subcategory your
      displayed content item belongs to overrides the options of its parent
      category.</para>

      <para>The next level is the <emphasis role="bold">content
      item</emphasis> level, e.g. an Article. The content item options
      override the options set in its category, the category's parent
      categories, and the base set.</para>

      <para>The most specific level is the <emphasis role="bold">menu
      item</emphasis>. THe menu item options override the options set in the
      content item, the content item's category, the category's parent
      categories, and the base set.</para>

      <para>At each of the more specific levels (category, content item, menu
      item) you can choose whether to enable overrides at all or not. This
      makes it easy to disable all overrides without having to click through
      each available option. Do note that Joomla doesn't have that; it asks
      you to click through each option individually which is arduous, and
      error prone.</para>

      <para>Moreover, each option which can be overridden either has a "Use
      Global" option, or allows you to leave it blank. These values signal to
      SocialMagick that it should fall back to the previous level of
      specificity to find the option value.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The component Options and the Template do not have "Use Global"
        as they are the <emphasis>base</emphasis> level, i.e. the least
        specific level. There is no previous level of specificity to fall back
        to. They are the bottom rung of the ladder already!</para>
      </note>

      <para>This scheme is very similar to how Joomla article options work
      <emphasis>in category list or category blog views</emphasis>. If you
      understand that, you are ready to handle SocialMagick options.</para>

      <para><emphasis>Side note: Joomla's Single Article menu items give you
      the wrong idea of how content options work</emphasis>. Joomla's Single
      Article menu items only apply options from the menu item, and the
      Options of the Articles (<code>com_content</code>) component. They
      IGNORE the options set in the article itself, the article's category,
      and the category's parent categories if any. This has led to chronic
      confusion among people who mistakenly think that component options
      override article or category options. <emphasis>This is not the
      case!</emphasis> The article and category options are NOT overridden by
      component options, they are simply completely ignored by the Single
      Article menu item. The article and category options are only applied
      when you use a Category Blog, Category List, Archived Articles, or
      Featured Articles menu item i.e. <emphasis>a menu item which is meant to
      show more than one article at a time</emphasis>. If you have been
      confused by this in the past, you need to recalibrate your mental model
      of how Joomla works. As to why there is this discrepancy: it's for
      backwards compatibility reasons. Single Article menu items worked like
      that in Joomla! 1.0 and its predecessor, Mambo. Changing how these menu
      items work would break sites, which is why it's never changed.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="installation-updates-upgrades">
    <title>Installation, updates and upgrades</title>

    <section xml:id="installing">
      <title>Installing Akeeba SocialMagick</title>

      <para>Installing <application>Akeeba SocialMagick</application> is no
      different than installing any other <trademark
      class="registered">Joomla!</trademark> extension on your site. You can
      read the complete instructions for installing Joomla! extensions on the
      <link xlink:href="https://docs.joomla.org/Installing_an_extension"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">official help page</link>.
      Throughout this chapter we assume that you are familiar with these
      instructions and we will try not to duplicate them.</para>

      <caution>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">DO NOT EXTRACT THE ZIP FILE YOU DOWNLOAD
        FROM OUR SITE.</emphasis></para>

        <para>Akeeba SocialMagick is shipped as a <literal>package</literal>
        extension. This is a special type of Joomla extension which consists
        of several extensions, linked together. If you install the contained
        extensions individually, Joomla will not know they are meant to
        function as a coordinated set of extensions. As a result, it will not
        show you updates for Akeeba SocialMagick, and will tell you that it
        has no update information when you try to update to a newer version of
        Joomla!.</para>

        <para>If you have accidentally done that download the ZIP file from
        our site and install it, twice in a row, without uninstalling it
        before or in between. This will tell Joomla that the extensions you
        installed separately belong together and let it repair this link
        between the extensions in your database's
        <database>#__extensions</database> table, where
        <database>#__</database> is the table name prefix used by your
        site.</para>
      </caution>

      <section>
        <title>Installing or manually updating the extension</title>

        <para>We recommend using the Upload And Install method for installing
        SocialMagick, just like any other Joomla extension.</para>

        <para>Keep in mind that installing and updating Akeeba SocialMagick
        (and almost all Joomla! extensions) is actually the same thing. If you
        want to update Akeeba SocialMagick you <emphasis role="bold">MUST
        NOT</emphasis> uninstall it before installing the new version. When
        you uninstall Akeeba SocialMagick you will lose all your templates and
        component-level options. This is definitely something you do not want
        to happen! Instead, simply install the new version on top of the old
        one. Joomla! will figure out that you are doing an update and will
        treat it as such, automatically.</para>

        <tip>
          <para>If you find that after installing or updating Akeeba
          SocialMagick it is missing some features or doesn't work, please try
          installing the same version a second time, without uninstalling the
          component. The reason is that very few times the Joomla! extensions
          installer code gets confused and fails to copy some files or entire
          folders. By repeating the installation you force it to copy the
          missing files and folders, solving the problem.</para>
        </tip>

        <section xml:id="installing-upload">
          <title>Upload and install.</title>

          <para>You can download the latest installation packages our site's
          <link xlink:href="https://www.akeeba.com/downloads.html"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">download page</link>. If
          you have an older version of Joomla! or PHP please consult our <link
          xlink:href="https://www.akeeba.com/compatibility.html"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Compatibility page</link>
          to find the version of Akeeba SocialMagick compatible with your
          Joomla! and PHP versions. In either case click on the version you
          want to download and install.</para>

          <para>All Akeeba SocialMagick installation packages contain the
          component and all of its associated extensions. Installing it will
          install all of these items automatically. It can also be used to
          upgrade Akeeba SocialMagick; just install it
          <emphasis>without</emphasis> uninstalling the previous
          release.</para>

          <para>In any case, do not extract the ZIP files yet!</para>

          <warning>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Attention Mac OS X users</emphasis>!
            Safari, the default web server provided to you by Apple, is
            automatically extracting the ZIP file into a directory and removes
            the ZIP file. In order to install the extension through Joomla!'s
            extensions installer you must select that directory, right-click
            on it and select Compress to get a ZIP file of its
            contents.</para>
          </warning>

          <para>Log in to your site's administrator section. Click on
          <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Manage</guimenuitem>
          link on the top menu. Please click on the <guilabel>Upload Package
          File</guilabel> tab. Drag and drop the installation ZIP file you had
          previously downloaded to start the upload and the installation.
          After a short while, <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> will tell you
          that the component has been installed.</para>

          <warning>
            <para>Akeeba SocialMagick is a big extension. Some servers do not
            allow you to upload files that big. If this is the case you can
            follow <link
            xlink:href="https://www.akeeba.com/documentation/brs/troubleshooting.html"
            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">our installation
            troubleshooting instructions</link> under "You get an error about
            the package not being uploaded to the server".</para>

            <para>If you have WAMPServer (or any other prepackaged local
            server), please note that its default configuration does not allow
            files over 2Mb to be uploaded. To work around that you will need
            to modify your php.ini and restart the server. On WAMPserver
            left-click on the WAMP icon (the green W), click on
            <guimenu>PHP</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>php.ini</guimenuitem>. Find
            the line beginning with <code>upload_max_filesize</code>. Change
            it so that it reads:</para>

            <programlisting>upload_max_filesize = 6M</programlisting>

            <para>Save this file. Now, left-click on the WAMP icon, click on
            <guimenu>Apache</guimenu>, <guisubmenu>Service</guisubmenu>,
            <guimenuitem>Restart Service</guimenuitem> and you can now install
            the component. Editing the <filename>php.ini</filename> file
            should also work on all other servers, local and live
            alike.</para>
          </warning>

          <para>If the installation did not work, please take a look at <link
          xlink:href="https://www.akeeba.com/documentation/brs/troubleshooting.html"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">our installation
          troubleshooting instructions</link>.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="installation-troubleshoot">
          <title>Troubleshooting the installation</title>

          <para>Please note that extensions installation is performed by
          Joomla itself, not code that we have written ourselves. If you have
          a problem installing a Joomla extension of ours the root cause is in
          Joomla! and the way some of its functions work. While we don't offer
          support for generic installation issues, this page is meant to serve
          as a collection of the troubleshooting steps we'd follow on any site
          when any extension doesn't install correctly.</para>

          <bridgehead>You get an error about the package not being uploaded to
          the server</bridgehead>

          <para>The installation packages of our extensions are rather big,
          approaching 2Mb for the Professional versions. Many server have a
          maximum file upload size or a maximum POST request size which is too
          small – typically around 2MB – for our software to install. The best
          solution is to ask your host to set the following in the server's
          php.ini:</para>

          <programlisting>upload_max_filesize = 10M
post_max_size = 10M
</programlisting>

          <para>On most hosts you can place these lines in a file called
          <filename>.user.ini</filename> (not the leading dot) or
          <filename>php.ini</filename> in your site's
          <filename>administrator</filename> directory.</para>

          <para>If this is not possible, there's a good chance that the
          following lines in your <filename>.htaccess</filename> file may work
          on most servers:</para>

          <programlisting>php_value upload_max_filesize 10M
php_value post_max_size 10M
</programlisting>

          <para>There is also another alternative, but it won't work on all
          hosts: installation by URL. Please go to the Download section of our
          site and select the software and version you want to download. Click
          on View All files. Next to the "Download now" button for the
          installation package you will see a link called "DirectLink". Right
          click on it and select "Copy link address" (the exact phrase depends
          on the browser, but it should have to do about copying the link or
          its address / URL / location).</para>

          <para>Now go to your site's back-end, Extensions, Extensions Manager
          and find the Install from URL tab. Replace the contents of the
          "Install URL" field with the contents of your clipboard (the
          DirectLink URL you copied above) and click on the "Install" button
          next to this textbox. As long as your server supports installing
          extensions from URL the installation should go through.</para>

          <para>If this still doesn't help please read on for further
          troubleshooting tips</para>

          <bridgehead>"Install path does not exist"</bridgehead>

          <para>Joomla! requires the PHP Gzip and ZIP extensions to be
          installed. If either is not installed or if it's blocked then
          Joomla! will be unable to install extensions. Unfortunately, a
          cascade of unhandled errors inside Joomla! itself will cause it to
          come up with the unhelpful and disorienting "Install path does not
          exist" error message.</para>

          <para>Solution: ask your host to enabled the GZip and ZIP extensions
          in PHP. Furthermore, ask them to make sure that they are not
          blocking the functionality of these extensions e.g. by using
          <code>disable_functions</code> or <code>disable_classes</code> in
          their <filename>php.ini</filename> file.</para>

          <para>Please note that we routinely see hosts disabling functions
          <code>zip_open</code>, <code>gzuncompress</code>,
          <code>gzdeflate</code> and <code>gzdecode</code> for ostensible
          "security reasons". First of all Joomla! WILL NOT work properly when
          any of these functions is unavailable. Moreover and despite what
          your host tells you, disabling this functions does not increase your
          site's security in any conceivable way. If your host denies to
          unblock these functions please take your site to a different host
          that understands how server security really works.</para>

          <bridgehead>"Unable to write entry" or "Unable to create
          destination" error</bridgehead>

          <para>This error message comes from Joomla! and it means that there
          is a file or directory permissions issue. Unfortunately this message
          is very non-specific and provides no useful information for
          troubleshooting. This is something we reported to Joomla in
          September 2017 and was fixed for the most part but internal issues
          in the way the extensions installer work still prevent the correct
          path from being shown.</para>

          <para>In the meantime, all you can do is ask your host to make sure
          that all folders and files on your site are writeable by the user
          under which your site runs. This is not something you or us can do.
          Please do ask your host.</para>

          <para>If this doesn't help it might mean that you have reached the
          file system capacity of your server. Please note that your account
          on the server might have several limits:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Maximum total size of files and database data. This is the
              most common limit, e.g. your host telling you that you can use
              10G of space in total. Please remember that this includes your
              database data. Moreover, keep in mind that "unlimited" is a
              marketing term, not reality. Usually you get up to a certain
              size limit and you have to ask for more, explaining why.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Maximum number of files. This is usually NOT advertised,
              documented or visible anywhere. Many hosts will only allow you
              up to a maximum number of files, e.g. 100,000. If you try to
              exceed that count the file is not created / replaced, as if the
              permissions were not adequate to write to it. Please note that
              most times the host engineers will call it "inode count" because
              that's technically what they are limiting on your hosting user
              account. Each inode is a filesystem index entry and each file
              and folder on your site consumes one inode (that's not very
              accurate but it's a well enough description to understand what
              an inode is).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The physical disk size. All the aforementioned limits are
              great, but you cannot create files beyond the physical capacity
              of the disks on your server. Most modern hosts use virtualized,
              network attached storage to provide ever-expanding capacity on
              demand. However, some cheaper hosts and dedicated servers still
              have regular disks attached with finite storage limits.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The block count. Please remember that computer permanent
              storage cannot be allocated with a single byte granularity. It
              is allocated in blocks, typically 4KB to 32KB each. Think of it
              as an apartment building where everyone gets the same size ,
              four bedroom apartment regardless of whether they are single or
              a family of seven with a dog and two cats. This means that small
              files, whose size is nominally under one block, will occupy at
              least one block. Your host counts the disk space usage by the
              number of blocks you occupy but hosting control panels report
              the aggregated nominal sizes of the files. It is possible for
              the hosting control panel to report free space when you have
              reached the block limit of your hosting account.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Also remember that your hosting control panel does not
              report the limit information in real time. You may have already
              exceeded your limits but your control panel not having been
              updated with this information.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>If you are not sure about these limits please ask your
          host.</para>

          <bridgehead>Upgrading from Core to Professional</bridgehead>

          <para>In some cases we have seen that Joomla failed to copy all of
          the necessary files when upgrading from a Core to a Professional
          release or when installing a major update that spans major versions
          (e.g. 1.x to 2.y). If you believe this has happened to you please
          install our software twice in a row, without uninstalling it before
          or in between the subsequent installations.</para>

          <bridgehead>Check your Joomla! and PHP version</bridgehead>

          <para>We publish the compatibility of our software with Joomla! and
          PHP versions in the Compatibility page on our site. You can find a
          link on this page at the bottom of every page of our site.</para>

          <para>Please remember that the PHP version your site is using may be
          different than the PHP version your host reports in their hosting
          control panel. If unsure, please refer to Joomla's System
          Information page. If you need to upgrade your PHP version please
          consult your host. The exact method to do that varies by
          host.</para>

          <bridgehead>Checking your temporary directory</bridgehead>

          <para>First, we will have to make sure that you are using a valid
          temporary directory. Many sites are configured to use the
          system-wide (/tmp) directory or an invalid directory, causing
          installation problems.</para>

          <para>You can change your temporary directory from your site's
          Global Configuration page. You need to enter the full filesystem
          path to Joomla's <filename>tmp</filename> folder. This is typically
          something like <filename>/home/mysite/public_html/tmp</filename>. If
          unsure please ask your host. This information is not visible from
          within your site's administrator using any Joomla-provided feature
          and there is no way for us to know it.</para>

          <bridgehead>File ownership (Previously: Enable FTP)</bridgehead>

          <para>Some shared servers run PHP as an Apache module. As a result
          PHP runs under the same user as Apache which is a different user
          than the one your user account is owned and the one used when
          uploading files via FTP / SFTP. As a result you end up with mixed
          ownership of your files, making it often impossible to install or
          update extensions.</para>

          <para>Old Joomla versions (1.x, 2.x and 3.x) included a Global
          Configuration feature called “Enable FTP”. This feature would make
          Joomla go through FTP to write to any file, therefore all your files
          would be owned by the same user, your hosting account's user.
          However, this was a security issue since Joomla needed to store your
          FTP password in the clear. In most cases that was also the hosting
          control panel password. In other words, any security mishap which
          would divulge Joomla's configuration to an unauthorised user — even
          a simple misconfiguration of your site's permissions — could cause
          major problems to your site. This feature has, therefore, been
          removed from Joomla 4.0 onwards.</para>

          <para>If you find yourself on such a host it's a good time to move
          to a different, better set up host.</para>

          <para>To give you a better idea, the PHP developers themselves have
          said that the PHP Apache module should not be used for shared
          hosting scenarios. It's something only really meant to be used for
          single site servers with the assumption that Apache is correctly
          configured for this use case. Solutions for PHP running as a
          different user for each site of a shared hosting server have existed
          since the early 00's. If your host has still not gotten wind of
          these problems and their respective solutions over a course of at
          least two decades they are probably unqualified to host any site,
          hence the recommendation to move to a different host.</para>

          <bridgehead>Still problems?</bridgehead>

          <para>If you still can't install our software and you are receiving
          messages regarding unwritable directories, inability to move files
          or other similar file system related error messages you can ask for
          our support but you already read what we're going to try. At best
          you can expect us to find out the most likely root cause and tell
          you what you have to ask your host to do to fix it.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="update">
      <title>Automatic updates</title>

      <para>Akeeba SocialMagick can be updated just like any other Joomla!
      extension, using the Joomla! extensions update feature. Please note that
      Joomla! is fully responsible for discovering available updates and
      installing them on your site. Akeeba Ltd does not have any control of
      the update process.</para>

      <note>
        <para>This Joomla! feature requires that your server supports fopen()
        URL wrappers (<option>allow_url_fopen</option> is set to 1 in your
        server's <filename>php.ini</filename> file) or has the PHP cURL
        extension enabled. Moreover, if your server has a firewall, it has to
        allow TCP connections over port 443 (HTTPS) to
        <uri>www.akeeba.com</uri> and <uri>cdn.akeeba.com</uri>. If you don't
        see any updates or if they fail to download please ask your host to
        check that these conditions are met. If they are met but you still do
        not see the updates please file a bug report in the <link
        xlink:href="http://forum.joomla.org/"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">official Joomla!
        forum</link>. In the meantime you can use the manual update methods
        discussed further below this page.</para>
      </note>

      <warning>
        <para>Akeeba SocialMagick needs you to set up the Download ID before
        you can install the updates. Please consult the <link
        linkend="update-dlid">Entering your Download ID</link> documentation
        section for more information.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>You can access the extensions update feature in different
      ways:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>From the icon your Joomla! administrator control panel page.
          By default you will find the icon in the right-hand modules area,
          under the <guilabel>Update Checks</guilabel> header. When there are
          updates found for any of your extensions you will see the
          <guilabel>Updates are available</guilabel> message. Clicking on it
          will get you to the Update page of Joomla! Extensions
          Manager.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>From the sidebar of your Joomla! Administrator click on
          <guimenu>System</guimenu>. On the new page find the
          <guilabel>Update</guilabel> area towards the bottom of the middle
          column and click the <guimenuitem>Extensions</guimenuitem> link.
          This takes you to the Update page of Joomla! Extensions
          Manager.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If you do not see the updates try clicking on the <guibutton>Find
      Updates</guibutton> button in the toolbar of the Joomla! Extensions:
      Update page. If you do not see the updates still you may want to wait up
      to 24 hours before retrying. This has to do with the way the update CDN
      works and how Joomla! caches the update information.</para>

      <para>If there is an update available for Akeeba SocialMagick tick the
      box to the left of its row and then click on the
      <guibutton>Update</guibutton> button in the toolbar. Joomla will now
      download and install the update.</para>

      <para>If Joomla can't download the package, please use one of the manual
      update methods described below.</para>

      <para>If you get a white page while installing the update please try
      either the Built-in method (described above) or the manual update method
      (described below).</para>

      <bridgehead>Updating manually</bridgehead>

      <para>As noted in the <link linkend="installing">installation
      section</link>, installing and updating Akeeba SocialMagick is actually
      the same thing. If the automatic update using Joomla!'s extensions
      update feature does not work, please install the update manually
      following the instructions in the <link
      linkend="installing">installation section of this
      documentation</link>.</para>

      <important>
        <para>When installing an update manually you MUST NOT uninstall your
        existing version of Akeeba SocialMagick. Uninstalling Akeeba
        SocialMagick will always remove all your settings. You definitely do
        not want that to happen!</para>
      </important>

      <para>Sometimes Joomla! may forget to copy some files when updating
      extensions. If you find Akeeba SocialMagick suddenly not working or if
      you get a warning that your installation is corrupt you need to download
      the latest version's ZIP file and install it <emphasis>twice</emphasis>
      on your site, <emphasis>without</emphasis> uninstalling it before or
      in-between these installations. This will most certainly fix this
      issue.</para>

      <para>If the error occurs again after a while, without you updating our
      software, please contact your host. Some hosts will delete or rename
      files automatically and without any confirmation as part of a (broken
      and unfit for purpose) "malware scanner / antivirus". Unfortunately,
      these scanners return a lot of false positives -innocent files
      mistakenly marked as malicious- but rename / delete them nonetheless,
      breaking software installed on the server. If you are on such a host we
      very strongly recommend that you move to a decent host, run by people
      who actually know what they are doing. It will be far less headache for
      you and would actually improve your site's security.</para>

      <section xml:id="update-troubleshooting">
        <title>Troubleshooting the update</title>

        <para>Like most Joomla extensions, our software relies on Joomla's
        built-in extensions updater. In simple terms, code written by the
        Joomla project, shipped with Joomla itself and running on your site is
        responsible for retrieving information about the latest available
        versions, determining whether an update is available, downloading the
        update package and installing it on your site. Akeeba Ltd has no
        control over that code.</para>

        <para>Despite this not being our code, we do understand that our
        clients do come across problems with updates and need our help. The
        way the Joomla built-in extensions updater is written makes it prone
        to some easily preventable, common errors. Its error reporting ranges
        from unhelpful to non-existent. In an effort to help you, we've
        compiled and condensed all the troubleshooting we've done for years on
        our sites and our clients' sites.</para>

        <para>Please note that we do not have a choice on whether to use
        Joomla's built-in extensions updater or our own code. The Joomla
        Extensions Direction requires us to use Joomla's own extensions
        updater as a requirement for our software being listed there.</para>

        <section xml:id="update-troubleshooting-server-issues">
          <title>Addressing server issues</title>

          <para>In some cases you will see that Joomla cannot retrieve the
          latest version information or update package for our software,
          reporting it cannot connect to cdn.akeeba.com. Related to that,
          Joomla may report that it's unable to download the Professional
          edition's update package, saying it's unable to connect to our site
          www.akeeba.com. This can mean a few different things which all have
          to do with how your host is set up.</para>

          <para>Our CDN and our site are accessible over HTTPS and use a
          valid, signed TLS certificate. At the time of this writing the TLS
          certificates are issued by Let's Encrypt and Amazon Web Services.
          The TLS certificates used for HTTPS on our CDN and site use the
          recommended SHA-256 hashing algorithm and the servers only support
          modern versions of the TLS protocol (at the time of this writing
          it's TLS 1.2 and later). If your host has an out of date
          Certification Authority cache or compiled PHP against an old TLS
          library which does not support modern versions of TLS your site will
          be unable to connect to our servers.</para>

          <para>If this is not the case, please be aware that some hosts run a
          proxy server or a firewall which can either prevent or cache
          <emphasis>outgoing</emphasis> connections in front of their servers.
          Depending on how this is implemented it can cause two distinct types
          of problems.</para>

          <para>The first problem is that your site might be unable to connect
          to our CDN and our server to retrieve the latest version information
          and the update package itself respectively. If this happens you need
          to ask your host to allow connections to TCP/IP port 443 (HTTPS) for
          www.akeeba.com and cdn.akeeba.com. If they ask you for an IP address
          please ask them to resolve these domain names from their server. The
          latter is a Content Delivery network (CDN) with hundreds of servers,
          powered by Amazon CloudFront, meaning that its IP address depends on
          where you are accessing it from.</para>

          <para>The second problem is that when Joomla tries to retrieve the
          latest version information or an update file from our servers your
          host's proxy gets in the way and returns information it has cached.
          We explicitly ask for that information not to be cached, using
          standard HTTP headers, but some hosts choose to ignore web standards
          and do their own thing. Also worth noting is that your host should
          not interfering with HTTPS (encrypted) traffic, so all the more
          reason to be worried about their implementation in this case.
          Unfortunately, we have caught a few hosts doing that over the
          years.</para>

          <para>None of these issues can be addressed by you or us. You will
          need to contact your host about them. Before you assume any of these
          issues are in play and if you are using the Professional edition of
          our software please do <link
          linkend="update-troubleshooting-dlid">check that your Download ID is
          valid</link> first.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="update-troubleshooting-dlid">
          <title>Check the validity of your Download ID</title>

          <note>
            <para>The information in this section only applies to the
            Professional edition. If you are using the Core edition you can
            skip over it.</para>
          </note>

          <para>If you are using the Professional version of our software we
          need to verify that you have an active subscription that gives you
          access to downloads of the software you are trying to update. We do
          that by means of a Download ID which has the format
          0123456789abcdef0123456789abcdef (Main Download ID) or
          12345:0123456789abcdef0123456789abcdef (Add-on Download ID). In and
          by itself the Download ID does not carry any information about your
          subscription status. It is an identifier linked to your account on
          our site.</para>

          <para>First, you need to check that you are using a valid Download
          ID. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that your Download
          ID</emphasis> is entered at all, or that it is valid. This kind of
          false assumption accounts for half of the update issues we are asked
          to help our clients with. Always check on our site. Log into our
          site and go to Add-on Download IDs from the top menu. Copy the
          Download ID and paste it to our extension's Options page in the
          Download ID box, under the Update tab.</para>

          <para>If you had to enter or change the Download ID but Joomla was
          already reporting an updated version you will need to wait for 1-2
          days OR install the update manually. This has to do with how Joomla
          update information caching works — even if you tell it to clear the
          update cache.</para>

          <section xml:id="dlid-check-subscription">
            <title>Check your subscription status</title>

            <note>
              <para>The information in this section only applies to the
              Professional edition. If you are using the Core edition you can
              skip over it.</para>
            </note>

            <para>As noted above, the Download ID itself does not carry any
            information about whether you are allowed to download an update.
            This check is done on our server when it receives the Download ID
            along with Joomla's request to download an update. The check
            performed is simple: do you have an <emphasis>active</emphasis>
            subscription which gives you access to the software you are trying
            to download?</para>

            <para>Do not assume that your subscription is active. It is
            possible that you missed an email warning you about the
            subscription expiring and a manual action to renew it being
            required on your part. Do note that we send two emails before your
            subscription reaches it validity limit and you lose access to
            downloads, 30 and 15 days in advance.</para>

            <para>Always log into our site and go to the My Subscriptions page
            to check your subscription status. If your subscription has
            expired you can renew it. Once the payment is complete and
            accepted by our reseller you will be able to download the updates
            within the next 20' or less (typically: within seconds).</para>
          </section>

          <section xml:id="dlid-multiple-pro-versions">
            <title>Multiple Professional edition Akeeba extensions with
            different Download IDs</title>

            <para>It's possible that you have more than one of our
            Professional extensions but you want to use different Download IDs
            for each one of them. For example, if each extension was bought by
            a different company working on your site or if you are trying to
            migrate to a new user account on our site.</para>

            <para>That is to say, one extension might use a Download ID that
            is valid and corresponds to an active subscription for that
            software, another extension might have an invalid Download ID or
            use a Download ID which refers to a user account on our site which
            does NOT have a valid subscription for that software.</para>

            <para>Do remember to check the Download IDs for each and every of
            our extensions. Do remember to check that you have active
            subscriptions for all the products you are trying to
            update.</para>
          </section>

          <section xml:id="dlid-change-after-update">
            <title>Entering or changing your Download ID after an update is
            available</title>

            <para>On March 9th, 2021 we publicly and officially notified
            Joomla about known issues with their extensions updater when the
            Download Key is changed after an updated version has been
            detected. We had previously notified Joomla of these issues
            repeatedly, but privately, over the course of eight years. These
            issues are still not addressed.</para>

            <para>If you enter or change your Download ID after Joomla has
            already determined an update is available the new Download ID will
            NOT take effect on many sites. This has to do with the way Joomla
            is caching not only the update availability information but also
            the raw information about Update Sites and Download Keys it uses
            to determine if updates are available and how to download
            them.</para>

            <para>If you find yourself in this case we strongly recommend
            installing the update manually (download the new version and
            install it using Upload and Install over the old one) OR wait 1-2
            days before retrying. Kindly note that retrying after 1-2 days MAY
            STILL NOT WORK.</para>

            <para>We understand that this is especially disruptive if you are
            managing dozens or hundreds of sites. This is why we have been
            trying to convince Joomla to fix these issues since 2014. We have
            even gone as far as to point out exactly why these issues occur
            and how to fix them. That's the full extent of what we can do. It
            is ultimately Joomla's responsibility to take your needs seriously
            enough and include the <emphasis>three lines of code to fix these
            issues</emphasis>.</para>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="update-stuck-showing">
          <title>Updates are showing after installing the latest
          version</title>

          <para>Sometimes you might see that Joomla reports that the version
          you have installed or even a previous version is available as an
          update. This can mean three things:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Joomla's update cache is stuck. Please file a bug report
              to Joomla. We have already been reporting this privately since
              2014 and made an official, public issue report on March 9th,
              2021.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>You have a server issue connecting to our CDN. See the
              information on <link
              linkend="update-troubleshooting-server-issues">addressing server
              issues</link>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>You have found a bug in Joomla's built-in extensions
              updater. You need to contact <link
              xlink:href="https://forum.joomla.org"
              xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">the Joomla!
              forum</link>. Unfortunately there is nothing we can do about
              Joomla core bugs.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="update-stuck">
          <title>Updates not showing despite having an older version</title>

          <para>Sometimes you may see that Joomla refuses to report the
          availability of a new version of our software. This can mean four
          things:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The update site for our software is disabled. See the
              information on <link linkend="update-check-update-site">checking
              the update site</link>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Joomla's update cache is stuck. Please file a bug report
              to Joomla. We have already been reporting this privately since
              2014 and made an official, public issue report on March 9th,
              2021.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>You have a server issue connecting to our CDN. See the
              information on <link
              linkend="update-troubleshooting-server-issues">addressing server
              issues</link>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>You have found a bug in Joomla's built-in extensions
              updater. You need to contact <link
              xlink:href="https://forum.joomla.org"
              xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">the Joomla!
              forum</link>. Unfortunately there is nothing we can do about
              Joomla core bugs.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <section xml:id="update-check-update-site">
            <title>Check the update site</title>

            <para>First we are going to check if the Update Site is disabled.
            Go to the System menu item, find the Update area and click on the
            Update Sites link.</para>

            <para>On that page you will see a list of the update sites for the
            extensions you have installed on your site. If you see our
            software in that list – you may have to search for it – make sure
            it's published, i.e. there's a green checkmark in the Status
            column. If it's not already published publish it now. If you had
            to publish the Update Site you will have to install the latest
            version manually, on top of the old one. This is due to Joomla's
            caching of the information required to retrieve update
            information. In other words, for a period of a few hours to a few
            days Joomla might be unable to automatically detect the new
            version of our software.</para>

            <para>If our software does not appear on that list you will need
            to click on Rebuild. Watch out, though! Joomla has a bug. When
            using Rebuild <emphasis role="bold">removes</emphasis> all
            Download IDs and Download Keys from all installed extensions on
            your site and will cause extension installation to fail. You will
            also need to follow the instructions under <link
            linkend="update-troubleshooting-dlid">Check the validity of your
            Download ID</link> for your updates to work.</para>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="update-misc">
          <title>Miscellaneous troubleshooting and information</title>

          <section xml:id="update-fail-download">
            <title>The update fails to download</title>

            <para>If you are trying to update a Professional edition please
            <link linkend="update-troubleshooting-dlid">check your Download
            ID</link>. Typically you will get an error message telling you
            that an error 403 or 500 was received when trying to download the
            update package. Whether you see that message or a generic download
            failure message depends on the version of Joomla you have
            installed on your site.</para>

            <para>If this doesn't help you need to check <link
            linkend="update-troubleshooting-server-issues">if you have a
            server issue</link>.</para>
          </section>

          <section xml:id="update-3pd-fail">
            <title>Updating with a third party service fails</title>

            <para>Typically, third party site management services ask Joomla
            to provide the update information and install update on your
            behalf. Therefore the troubleshooting information in this section
            would solve both in-site and remote (via a service) extension
            updates.</para>

            <para>If you can install an update by logging into your site's
            backend but NOT through a service you need to contact the third
            party site management service and report this issue. Unfortunately
            we cannot help with it. Third party services DO NOT ask us for
            permission to implement an updater for our software.</para>
          </section>

          <section xml:id="update-manual">
            <title>Manual update</title>

            <para>As noted earlier in the documentation, a manual update is
            the same as installing the extension. Download the latest version
            from our site and install it on your site <emphasis
            role="bold">without</emphasis> uninstalling our extension.</para>
          </section>

          <section xml:id="update-installation-fail">
            <title>Update installation problems</title>

            <para>If your update does download but fails to install try the
            manual update method (installing the new version on top of the old
            one). If that fails, too, you should follow the instructions on
            the installation troubleshooting section you can read earlier in
            this documentation.</para>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="update-dlid">
        <title>Entering your Download ID</title>

        <para>Akeeba SocialMagick is distributed for-a-fee. Downloading it,
        either for installation from scratch or as an update to an already
        installed but older version on your site, requires confirming that you
        have an active subscription which gives you access to Akeeba
        SocialMagick downloads. When you download the installation ZIP file
        from our site this means that you need to log in to our site first.
        However, when downloading updates through Joomla you really don't want
        to and usually cannot be asked to log in to our site. The Download ID
        is used in this case to identify you to our download servers.
        Furthermore, a Download ID linked with an active subscription is also
        required to use some remote file storage services such as Dropbox and
        OneDrive (specifically: any remote storage service which uses OAuth2
        or a variation thereof, therefore requiring a special “mediator”
        script which runs on our servers).</para>

        <para><bridgehead>Using your Download IDs on your clients'
        sites</bridgehead></para>

        <para>Our software license allows you to use your Download IDs on the
        sites of your clients. However, you must tell your clients
        that:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Downloads and support for the software covered by the
            Download ID is provided by you, not Akeeba Ltd.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If they want to receive support and / or downloads directly
            from Akeeba Ltd they need to purchase a qualifying subscription on
            our site. In this case they do not qualify for the renewal
            discount.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>They are not allowed to use the Download ID on any other
            site or use the Download ID to download the software for any
            reason other than updating or reinstalling the covered software on
            the same site the Download ID was entered in. In other words, they
            cannot use the Download ID to install or update our software on
            any other site.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If you are no longer administering a site where you have entered
        a Download ID you must revoke or regenerate that Download ID. You need
        to do the same if you believe that your Download ID is being used by
        third parties in an unauthorized manner. Please note that unauthorized
        use of Download IDs could have consequences with regards to your
        subscription with us.</para>

        <bridgehead>Finding your Download ID</bridgehead>

        <para>Download IDs come in two flavors, your main Download ID and
        Add-on Download IDs.</para>

        <para>You can find your main Download ID in the <link
        xlink:href="https://www.akeeba.com/my-subscriptions.html"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">My Subscriptions</link>
        page of our site. We recommend using this Download ID only on your own
        site(s). This Download ID cannot be revoked, it can only be
        regenerated. If it's regenerated you will need to enter the new
        Download ID on all of your sites which can be a significant
        hassle.</para>

        <para>You can generate an unlimited number of Add-on Download IDs
        without additional charge in the <link
        xlink:href="https://www.akeeba.com/download/add-on-dlid.html"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Add-on Download IDs</link>
        page. Unlike the main Download ID you can revoke (disable) any Add-on
        Download ID at any time. As long as you only use one Add-on Download
        ID per site revoking or regenerating it will not affect the other
        sites' ability to download and install updates.</para>

        <para><bridgehead>Enter or view your Download ID</bridgehead></para>

        <para>From the main administrator page of your site click on System on
        the sidebar.</para>

        <para>Click on the Update Sites link towards the bottom of the middle
        column on the System page.</para>

        <para>Find the <guilabel>Akeeba SocialMagick package</guilabel> entry
        on the list and click on it to open the edit page.</para>

        <para>Enter your main or Add-on Download ID in the Download Key area.
        Click on the Save &amp; Close button on the toolbar to apply the
        Download ID.</para>

        <para>If Akeeba SocialMagick or Joomla! was already showing you that
        an update for Akeeba SocialMagick is available you will need to
        install the update manually.</para>

        <bridgehead>Troubleshooting updates to the Professional
        release</bridgehead>

        <para>If you still cannot install our software please check that the
        Download ID is entered correctly. If it's not entered correctly enter
        the correct Download ID and follow all of these instructions
        again.</para>

        <para>If the Download ID is entered correctly but it's not active in
        the Add-on Download IDs page you will need to enable it. After
        enabling it you will be able to download and install the update
        <emphasis>without</emphasis> having to follow these instructions
        again.</para>

        <para>If the Download ID is correct please make sure that you have an
        <emphasis>active</emphasis> qualifying subscription on our site. If
        your subscription has expired you need to purchase a renewal on our
        site. Once the renewal is active you will be able to download and
        install the update <emphasis>without</emphasis> having to follow these
        instructions again, as long as you have not changed your Download
        ID.</para>

        <para>If you still cannot download updates despite having the correct
        Download ID and an active subscription try waiting for 24 to 48 hours.
        In very rare cases Joomla's update cache gets stuck despite following
        the instructions above and you just need to wait until Joomla decides
        it has to reload it.</para>

        <para>If the updates are still not downloading please make sure that
        you are using a version of Joomla and PHP that is supported by the new
        version of our software. If you are not sure please consult <link
        xlink:href="https://www.akeeba.com/compatibility.html"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">our Compatibility
        page</link>.</para>

        <para>If you've followed all these troubleshooting steps and the
        update is not downloading at all you need to contact your host and ask
        them to allow traffic to <uri>www.akeeba.com</uri> and
        <uri>cdn.akeeba.com</uri> over port TCP 443 (HTTPS), make sure that
        the PHP cURL module is installed and activated on the version of PHP
        your site is using and that finally the libcurl and libssl system
        libraries the cURL module is compiled against are up-to-date versions.
        If your host cannot help you with any of these requests (despite this
        being literally what you are paying them to do) you can install
        updates manually. Kindly note that Akeeba Ltd is not responsible for
        your hosting environment and that the requirements for downloading
        updates from our site are met by server software released roughly 5
        years ago. If your host cannot provide 5 year old software and open
        ports in their firewall you should probably be migrating your site to
        a more up-to-date, competent host.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="downgrade">
      <title>Downgrades</title>

      <para>Downgrades <emphasis role="bold">ARE NOT
      SUPPORTED</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>If you downgrade Akeeba SocialMagick to a previous version we
      cannot guarantee it will work correctly. If you need to downgrade Akeeba
      SocialMagick you need to <link linkend="uninstalling">uninstall
      it</link> first.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="uninstalling">
      <title>Uninstalling Akeeba SocialMagick</title>

      <para>Akeeba SocialMagick can be uninstalled just like any other Joomla
      extension.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>Uninstalling Akeeba SocialMagick will delete your templates, any
        any generated OpenGraph images. There is no further confirmation. This
        process is <emphasis role="bold">IRREVERSIBLE</emphasis>. If you lose
        your settings and images by uninstalling Akeeba SocialMagick we cannot
        help you retrieve them, they are gone forever.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>First, go the extensions manager page. From the sidebar of your
      Joomla! Administrator click on <guimenu>System</guimenu>. On the new
      page find the <guilabel>Manage</guilabel> area towards the top of the
      middle column and click the <guimenuitem>Extensions</guimenuitem>
      link.</para>

      <para>In the Search box type <guilabel>Akeeba SocialMagick
      package</guilabel>. It will show you a single item called "Akeeba
      SocialMagick package" whose Type is Package.</para>

      <important>
        <para>Only ever try to uninstall the Package type extension. DO NOT
        try to uninstall the component, its plugins or module individually. It
        will leave stuff behind.</para>
      </important>

      <para>Select the item's checkbox and click on the
      <guibutton>Uninstall</guibutton> button in the toolbar. The extension
      and all its dependencies will be automatically uninstalled.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="requesting-support">
      <title>Requesting support and reporting bugs</title>

      <para>Support can be provided only to subscribers and only through our
      site's Support section. If you already have an active subscription which
      gives you access to the support for Akeeba SocialMagick you can request
      support for it through our site. You will need to log in to our site and
      go to Support, Akeeba SocialMagick and click on the <guibutton>New
      Ticket</guibutton> button. If you can't see the button please make sure
      you have an active subscription that gives you access to Akeeba
      SocialMagick support. If you do and still don't see the button please
      use the Contact Us page to let us know of the ticket system problem and
      remember to tell us your username.</para>

      <para>If you want to report a bug, please use the Contact Us page of our
      site. You don't need to be a subscriber to report a bug. Please note
      that unsolicited support requests sent through the Contact Us page will
      not be addressed. An issue is not a bug unless it can be reliably
      reproduced <emphasis>on multiple sites and servers</emphasis>. Please
      make sure you include clear instructions on reproducing the issue. If
      the issue cannot be reproduced it's not a bug report, it's a support
      request.</para>

      <important>
        <para>Support cannot be provided over Twitter, Facebook, email,
        telephone, the official Joomla! forum, our Contact Us page or any
        other method except the Support section on our site. We also cannot
        take bug reports over any other medium except the Contact Us page and
        the Support section on our site. Support is not provided to
        non-subscribers. We have to impose those restrictions in support to
        ensure a high level of service and quality. Thank you for your
        understanding.</para>
      </important>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="templates">
    <title>The templates</title>

    <para>SocialMagick generates OpenGraph images by combining one or more of
    a solid / semi-transparent colour card, an image of your choice, an image
    from your content (e.g. the intro, full article, or category image) or a
    static image, and text (content title, or static text). Which of these
    items are applied, how they are applied, and in which order is defined in
    a Template.</para>

    <section xml:id="template-preview">
      <title>Preview</title>

      <para>Setting up an OpenGraph image template would normally require a
      good understanding of how compositing works, and a fair amount of
      guesswork as to how it will all get combined together into an image.
      This is a tall order, and users would regularly tweak the template, go
      to the frontend to generate a new image, look at the page source code
      for the image URL, open that URL, inspect the image, rinse and repeat
      until the desired results are achieved. This was a gruelling
      process.</para>

      <para>But not anymore.</para>

      <para>SocialMagick now comes with a template preview. It uses a
      selection of sample images to be used as the Extra Image (assuming this
      option is set to neither None nor Static), and custom text of your
      choice to render an OpenGraph image using your template options
      <emphasis>as you are editing the template</emphasis>. You don't even
      have to save your template; it picks up the options on the template edit
      page. You can even enable the <link linkend="debug-text-layout">debug
      text layout</link> feature just for the preview –instead of at the
      component Options level– to fine-tune the placement of your overlay text
      on the template!</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/template-preview.png" scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>You can collapse (hide) the template preview by clicking on the
      Show / Hide Preview icon found on the header of the <guilabel>Template
      Preview</guilabel> area.</para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Sample Extra Image</guilabel> lets you choose one of
      the predefined images shipped with SocialMagick as a stand-in for your
      template's Extra Image as long as your <guilabel>Extra Image
      Source</guilabel> is set to anything other than <option>None</option> or
      <option>Static Image</option>. The available images are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Alipazani</option>. Portrait image, with the focus
          towards the top-right of the image.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Erensever</option>. A square image with several
          subjects in the foreground.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Olly</option>. A landscape image with the subject on
          the left.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Xtrovarts</option>. A landscape image with the subject
          on the right.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Danxavier</option>. A landscape image with the subject
          on the centre.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Lindsey</option>. A vertical panorama (much taller
          than wide) image.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Spiske</option>. A horizontal panorama (much wider
          than tall) image.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The images were selected so that they cover the vast majority of
      photographs we have seen used on real world sites. The images, and the
      JSON file with their definition, is in
      <filename>media/com_socialmagick/images/examples</filename>. Please note
      that if you decide to edit those files, they will be overwritten next
      time you update the extension.</para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Sample Text</guilabel> will be used as a stand-in
      for the overlay text source. We recommend using text that is about the
      same length and in the same language as the text you're going to use in
      your content and menu items.</para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Debug Text Layout</guilabel> will turn on the <link
      linkend="debug-text-layout">debug text layout</link> feature when
      rendering the image. As you can see in the screenshot above, it renders
      the textbox (with a recommended padding area) and the individual text
      lines' bounding boxes so that you can understand why the text ended up
      where it is, and why it's rendered the way it is. We have found this to
      be one of the most time-saving features when trying to compose a
      visually interesting OpenGraph image.</para>

      <para>After making changes to your template's configuration click on
      <guibutton>Refresh preview</guibutton> to generate a new preview image
      <emphasis>without</emphasis> having to save the changes to the template.
      This is very useful if you are editing a template already in use; you
      don't want to save the template –causing all existing OpenGraph images
      to be generated again with the new template– before you are certain your
      changes work the way you want them to!</para>

      <para>The preview image is rendered in a fairly small size. If you want
      to inspect it in detail, click on <guibutton>Open image in new
      tab</guibutton> to open the image file in a new browser tab.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="template-size">
      <title>Size</title>

      <para>At its core, an OpenGraph image is defined by its dimensions,
      <guilabel>Width</guilabel> and <guilabel>Height</guilabel>. They are
      measured in pixels.</para>

      <para>The recommended size for each platform is different depending on
      where the image is used. That said, a size of 1200 by 640 pixels is a
      good size and the correct aspect ration for most if not all use cases.
      That's why it is set as the default for built-in and new
      templates.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="template-composition">
      <title>Image composition</title>

      <para>SocialMagick composites the image by combining items on top of
      each other. The available items used in compositing are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Colour</emphasis>. The entire layer is
          filled with a solid or semi-transparent colour. You can select its
          opacity, from 0 (fully transparent, i.e. does not show up) to 100
          (fully opaque). This colour can only be defined in the template; it
          cannot be overridden.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Base Image</emphasis>. An optional
          static image. You can use it to apply frames and branding to your
          template. This image can only be defined in the template; it cannot
          be overridden.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Extra Image</emphasis>. An optional
          image which may come from the content (intro image, full article
          image, category image, …), a <link
          xlink:href="https://docs.joomla.org/J5.x:Adding_custom_fields"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Joomla Field</link>
          (a.k.a. Custom Field), or a static image you select. This image can
          be overridden in more specific option levels.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Text</emphasis>. Optional text which may
          come from the content (article title, category title, …), or static
          text you enter. This text can be overridden in more specific option
          levels.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>The Base Image and Extra Image can be any graphics format
        supported by your PHP image library. Typically, files in the PNG, JPG,
        GIF, and BMP formats are safe to use. Most servers do support WebP
        images, as well as some other lesser known formats you are unlikely to
        be using on your site such as TIFF, XCF, and so on.</para>

        <para>Do not use animated images. In most cases only the first frame
        will be used. In some extreme cases, you might get an error, thus no
        image generated.</para>

        <para>SVG files are supported only by the <code>imagick</code>
        extension; the <code>gd</code> extension does not support them at all.
        Moreover, SVGs are rendered in the image size they claim to be; they
        are not scaled up or down to the template size. This can cause a lot
        of display artifacts. As a result, we recommend converting your SVGs
        to PNG or WebP images at a size suitable for your template
        size.</para>
      </note>

      <para>The items are layered on top of each other. If you have ever used
      a graphics application, you will immediately recognise that it is
      exactly how all non-trivial graphics applications work. If you are new
      to this concept, you can think of it like printing on transparency film,
      and layering the transparencies on top of each other, then looking
      through from the bottom to the top of the transparencies stack. The
      layers stack looks like this:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/layering.png" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The bottommost layer (1) is the <emphasis
      role="bold">Underlay</emphasis> layer. The Extra Image will be placed
      here the <guilabel>Display Layer</guilabel> option is set to
      <option>Underlay</option>.</para>

      <para>The second layer from the bottom (2) is the <emphasis
      role="bold">Colour</emphasis> layer. This is where the Colour is applied
      to. If you do not want to use this layer, set the <guilabel>Background
      Colour Opacity</guilabel> option to <option>0</option> (all the way to
      the left).</para>

      <para>The middle layer (3) is the <emphasis role="bold">Base
      Image</emphasis> layer. This is where the Base Image is placed.</para>

      <para>The fourth layer (4) is the <emphasis
      role="bold">Overlay</emphasis> layer. The Extra Image will be placed
      here the <guilabel>Display Layer</guilabel> option is set to
      <option>Overlay</option>.</para>

      <para>The topmost layer (5) is the <emphasis role="bold">Text</emphasis>
      layer. This is where the Text will be rendered.</para>

      <section xml:id="template-composition-examples">
        <title>Practical examples of composition</title>

        <para>SocialMagick comes with a number of predefined templates which
        show you a lot of practical use cases. Feel free to copy and customise
        them. Use the Template Preview feature to understand the effects of
        your changes.</para>

        <para>Beyond that, here are some further examples we have used on
        production sites.</para>

        <para><bridgehead>Colourise The Extra Image</bridgehead></para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/composition-colourised.png"
                       scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>Concept: The brand uses colourful images for its posts. For
        social sharing they wanted to mute the palette to the main brand
        colour to draw attention to the page title. Please note that what you
        see in the example image is not the brand's font, the correct font
        size, and text positioning used on the live site. We deliberately
        altered it to make the colourisation effect more pronounced.</para>

        <para>Implementation: To colourise the extra image we need to convert
        it to grayscale, and layer a semi-transparent colour layer on top of
        it.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Base background colour: #5cb0c9</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Background colour opacity: 27</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Extra Image, Grayscale: 100</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><bridgehead>Framing / Branding Without A Colour
        Background</bridgehead></para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/composition-framed.png" scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>Concept: This blog site is using big, colourful images for each
        post. For social sharing we want to surround them with a branded frame
        which has a "banner" area where we overlay the article's title.</para>

        <para>Implementation: Put the Extra Image in the background,
        overlaying a Base Image.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Background colour opacity: 0</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Base image: we used a PNG image which has the frame
            elements</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Extra Image, Display Layer: Underlay</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="template-colour">
      <title>Colour</title>

      <para>As noted in the previous section, the colour layer is just that:
      an entire layer filled with a specific color defined by the
      <guilabel>Base Background Colour</guilabel> option and the
      <guilabel>Background Colour Opacity</guilabel>.</para>

      <para>If you do not wish to use a background colour layer, set the
      <guilabel>Background Colour Opacity</guilabel> to 0. This makes the
      layer completely transparent, visually removing it from the composition
      of the image.</para>

      <para>The transparency is there to create visually interesting effects
      together with an Extra Image whose layer is set to Underlay (layer 1,
      behind the colour which is layer 2). If you do not use an underlay Extra
      Image and have an opacity lower than 100% the background of your image
      will be semitransparent. This may be problematic, as you cannot control
      which background color it will be rendered on. Most sites render images
      over a white background, but some may do that against a darker
      colour.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="template-base-image">
      <title>Base Image</title>

      <para>The Base Image lets you optionally define an image which is placed
      between the colour layer and the overlay layer. Typically, a Base Image
      is used to provide a frame around the image, branding elements, visually
      interesting text areas, etc. The image will be best fit to the template
      size.</para>

      <note>
        <para>"Best fit" is a combined resized and crop. If the image is
        smaller than both the width and height of the template it's left as
        is. Otherwise, it is resized to keep its aspect ratio whereas one of
        its dimensions fits the respective dimension of the template. The rest
        of the image not fitting in the template is cropped. This
        <emphasis>can</emphasis> lead to artifacts, therefore we strongly
        suggest that the image is created so that it has the same dimensions
        as your template.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Transparent and semitransparent areas of the image will let the
      layers below it (colour and underlay) to show through. You can use this
      to your advantage to create visually interesting effects. If you do not
      plan on using an underlay image or colour you should use a fully opaque
      image.</para>

      <para>You can apply effect on the image as well:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Grayscale. Removes the colour from the image without affecting
          its contrast and brightness. It can be from 0 (no effect) to 100
          (all colour removed). You can use intermediate values to mute
          colours towards a neutral black and white palette without removing
          all colour.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Sepia. Applies a sepia colour filter.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Opacity. Adjust the opacity of the image, from 0 (fully
          transparent) to 100 (fully opaque). Do note that semi-transparent
          areas of the image are kept at their current alpha (transparency)
          value at 100, and are made more transparent for lower values. This
          may result in some semi-transparent areas becoming fully transparent
          as you are decreasing this value.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In practice, you should avoid applying effects to the base image
      unless you are interested in watermarking extra images placed in the
      underlay layer. In this case you can use 100% grayscale and a low
      opacity (typically 8% or less) to create a watermark effect.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="template-extra-image">
      <title>Extra Image</title>

      <para>The Extra Image lets you define an image which can be used with
      (or without) the Base Image to create visually interesting compositions.
      The Extra Image can come from the content displayed on the page, or
      provided as a static image. The source of the Extra Image can be
      overridden in categories, content items, and menu items.</para>

      <para><guilabel>Add an Extra Image</guilabel> controls whether an Extra
      Image will be used at all. If this is disabled in your template, any
      further overrides to the Extra Image source in categories, content
      items, and menu items will NOT be taken into account.</para>

      <bridgehead>Extra Image Sources</bridgehead>

      <para>The <guilabel>Extra Image Source</guilabel> controls where the
      Extra Image comes from.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>None</option>. No Extra Image will be used. This is
          different than setting Add An Extra Image to No in that this Extra
          Image Source option CAN be overridden in categories, content items,
          and menu items.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Intro Image</option>. Uses the Intro Image of the
          content item. The exact semantics of this source depend on the
          integration plugin. Please read the Important box below.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Full Article Image</option>. Uses the Full Article
          Image of the content item. The exact semantics of this source depend
          on the integration plugin. Please read the Important box
          below.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Custom Field</option>. Uses a Joomla Custom Field
          defined on the content item. You can define the name of the custom
          field in the <guilabel>Extra Image Field Name</guilabel> option.
          Support for this depends on the integration plugin. Please read the
          Important box below.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Full Article, Or Intro Image</option>. Uses the Full
          Article Image source. If no image is defined there, it uses the
          Intro Image source.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Intro, Or Full Article Image</option>. Uses the Intro
          Image source. If no image is defined there, it uses the Full Article
          Image source.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Custom Field, Full Article, Or Intro Image</option>.
          Uses the Custom Field source. If no image is defined there, it uses
          the Full Article Image source. If no image is defined there, it uses
          the Intro Image source.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Custom Field, Intro, Or Full Article Image</option>.
          Uses the Custom Field source. If no image is defined there, it uses
          the Intro Image source. If no image is defined there, it uses the
          Full Article Image source.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Static Image</option>. The image source is not linked
          to the content. It comes from an image you define in the
          <guilabel>Static Image</guilabel> option.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <important>
        <para>SocialMagic has a plugin system for integrating with Joomla core
        and and third party extensions content. The appropriate integration
        plugin is used depending on the content being displayed on your site
        when the OpenGraph image is being generated. For example, if you are
        displaying a category blog for core content (articles) the
        SocialMagick - Content Categories plugin is used.</para>

        <para>The Custom Field, Intro Image, and Full Article Image sources
        have different meanings depending on the integration plugin being
        used. In the example above, Custom Field refers to a category field,
        whereas both Intro Image and Full Article Image both refer to the
        category's Image field. Conversely, if you are click on an article
        displayed in the category blog the SocialMagick - Articles integration
        plugin is used, in which case the Custom Field refers to an article
        field, and the Intro Image and Full Article Image refer to the
        respective fields in the article.</para>

        <para>The reason the template uses the generic terms "Intro Image",
        "Full Article Image", and "Custom Field" is because the same template
        can be used for radically different menu items corresponding to
        different integration plugins. The semantics of these sources for each
        integration plugins are documented in the <link
        linkend="socialmagick-plugins">integration plugins
        documentation</link> page.</para>
      </important>

      <para>The <guilabel>Extra Image Field Name</guilabel> option defines the
      Name of the Joomla custom field which holds the image filename. The
      field must be of type Media (or third party equivalent) or Text and it
      must point to <emphasis role="bold">an image file stored on your web
      server</emphasis>. If the field points to an image stored outside of
      your server (e.g. by using a third party plugin in the
      <code>filesystem</code> group) or a URL / URI <emphasis
      role="bold">SocialMagick cannot use it</emphasis>. That's for
      performance and reliability reasons. We have found that having an image
      on a slow remote storage provider (such as Amazon S3), a slow server,
      with an invalid URL, or experiencing network issues can make page loads
      take several seconds or even fail — both of which are detrimental to SEO
      and site reliability.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>The best approach to performance is to host your images on your
        web server and put your site behind a CDN, such as CloudFlare, to
        serve the static media efficiently. This greatly simplifies site
        management, allows you to use SocialMagick very efficiently, and helps
        your site load <emphasis>much</emphasis> faster.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>The <guilabel>Static Image</guilabel> option allows you to define
      an image on your site to use as the Extra Image Source. The image you
      select must be <emphasis role="bold">an image file stored on your web
      server</emphasis>. If the field points to an image stored outside of
      your server (e.g. by using a third party plugin in the
      <code>filesystem</code> group) or a URL / URI <emphasis
      role="bold">SocialMagick cannot use it</emphasis> for the reasons
      explained above.</para>

      <bridgehead>Display layer</bridgehead>

      <para>The <guilabel>Display Layer</guilabel> option lets you choose how
      SocialMagick will composite the Extra Image on the generated OpenGraph
      image.</para>

      <para>As explained earlier, <option>Underlay</option> puts the image in
      the underlay (bottommost) layer, under the colour background and Base
      Image. <option>Overlay</option> puts the image in the overlay layer
      above the Base Image and below the text (if any).</para>

      <para>Typically, you will use Underlay in combination with a Base Image
      that has a cutout (fully transparent) or semitransparent area, possibly
      with some resizing and cropping tweaking, to display parts of your Extra
      Image for a framing effect. Here's a typical example:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/composition-framed.png" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Conversely, the Overlay is used in two typical use cases. One, you
      want to completely or partially cover the Base Image. The example below
      is the same template as above but with the Display Layer switched from
      Underlay to Overlay.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/overlay-simple.png" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Two, you know your Extra Image has transparency, so you want it
      overlaid on the image but underneath the text for a watermark effect. In
      the example below, the shoeprint is a semi-transparent static image. We
      used the resizing and cropping parameters to move it to the lower right
      corner of the text box, creating this watermark effect.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/shoeprint.png" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <bridgehead>Resizing</bridgehead>

      <para>When <guilabel>Auto-Resize</guilabel> is set to
      <option>Yes</option> (default), SocialMagick uses an image fit algorithm
      called Best Fit (or Cover, as you know it from CSS). It roughly
      translates to these steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Extra Image is placed on the template surface depending on
          the <guilabel>Crop Anchor Point</guilabel> setting – we'll talk
          about it later.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the width <emphasis>or</emphasis> height of the Extra Image
          are equal or smaller than the width and height of the template, the
          image is left as-is. No further steps are considered. For example,
          let's consider a 300x200 template. If the image is 300x400 pixels no
          resizing takes place since the Extra Image is already the same width
          as the template.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The image is resized, with its aspect ratio kept intact, so
          either its width or its height matches the template's corresponding
          dimension and the resized does not become smaller than the
          template's area. For example, let's consider a 300x200 template. If
          the image is 600x600 pixels the choices we have is either make it a
          300x300 image (fit the width) or 200x200 image (fit the height).
          SocialMagick resizes to 300x300 since the 200x200 image would NOT
          cover the entire 300x200 template area (it would leave a 100x200
          area uncovered).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Any part of the resized Extra Image that's outside the
          template surface is cropped off.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>When <guilabel>Auto-Resize</guilabel> is set to
      <option>No</option> there are two changes.</para>

      <para>Instead of using the template's width and height, SocialMagick
      uses the dimensions you enter in <guilabel>Maximum Resize
      Width</guilabel> and <guilabel>Maximum Resize Height</guilabel>. These
      dimensions can be smaller or bigger than the template dimensions. You
      want to use a smaller size to shrink an image to make it fit into a
      cutout in the Base Image. You want to use a larger size to have a larger
      image to crop from, focusing on a detail on the image.</para>

      <para>You can also tell SocialMagick to move the <emphasis
      role="bold">resized</emphasis> Extra Image around the template area by
      using the <guilabel>X Position (From Left)</guilabel> and <guilabel>Y
      Position (From Top)</guilabel>. Think about it as having the resized
      Extra Image in the top left corner of the OpenGraph image, then dragging
      it this many pixels to the right and bottom respectively. This allows
      you to position the extra image in a cutout. This operation is known in
      graphics software as <emphasis role="bold">transform</emphasis>. It is
      important to remember that this leaves blank (transparent) space on the
      top and left of the Extra Image. For this reason, it typically only
      makes sense to use these transform options when there's a Base Image
      covering that area with its own content. You can use negative values to
      move the image towards the left or the top.</para>

      <para><bridgehead>Cropping</bridgehead></para>

      <para>As noted above, how the Extra Image is placed on the template
      surface depends on your <guilabel>Crop Anchor Point</guilabel> setting.
      The options are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Top Left</option>. The Extra Image is placed on the
          template surface so that the Extra Image's top left corner coincides
          with the template's top left corner.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Top</option>. The Extra Image is placed on the
          template surface so that the Extra Image's top middle point
          coincides with the template's top middle point.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Top Right</option>. The Extra Image is placed on the
          template surface so that the Extra Image's top right corner
          coincides with the template's top right corner.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Left</option>. The Extra Image is placed on the
          template surface so that the Extra Image's left middle point
          coincides with the template's left middle point.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Centre Point</option>. The Extra Image is placed on
          the template surface so that the Extra Image's dead center
          (horizontally and vertically) point coincides with the template's
          dead center point.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Right</option>. The Extra Image is placed on the
          template surface so that the Extra Image's right middle point
          coincides with the template's right middle point.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Bottom Left</option>. The Extra Image is placed on the
          template surface so that the Extra Image's bottom left corner
          coincides with the template's bottom left corner.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Bottom</option>. The Extra Image is placed on the
          template surface so that the Extra Image's bottom middle point
          coincides with the template's bottom middle point.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Bottom Right</option>. The Extra Image is placed on
          the template surface so that the Extra Image's bottom right corner
          coincides with the template's bottom right corner.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <important>
        <para>When <guilabel>Auto-Resize</guilabel> is set to Yes and the
        Extra Image is bigger than the template's dimensions, the corner
        options (top left, top right, bottom left, bottom right) are
        functionally identical to the four sides options – which one depends
        on the image's aspect ratio. That's because Auto-Resize uses the Best
        Fit (Cover) resize algorithm which <emphasis>guarantees</emphasis>
        that in this case either the width or the height of the resized image
        will be identical to the corresponding dimension of the
        template.</para>

        <para>If you think SocialMagick is broken because the corner options
        had no effect compared to the edge options, stop and think: "Do I have
        a resizing situation which makes one dimension of the resized image
        identical to the respective dimension of the template?". If the answer
        is "yes", SocialMagick did <emphasis>exactly what you told it to
        do</emphasis>, not what you wanted it to do. You probably want to set
        <guilabel>Auto-Resize</guilabel> to No and work on your resizing
        options to achieve the effect you were looking for.</para>

        <para>For example, let's consider a 300x200 template and a 900x900
        Extra Image. The resized Extra Image will be 300x300 templates, i.e.
        the width will be the same. Using the Top Left, Top, and Top Right
        options will produce the same effect. Since the width of the resized
        Extra Image and the template are now the same, placing the images so
        that their tops align also means that by definition their top left
        corner, top middle point, <emphasis>and</emphasis> top right corner
        coincide.</para>
      </important>

      <para>There are another two options called <guilabel>Crop Origin Nudge
      Towards Right</guilabel> and <guilabel>Crop Origin Nudge Towards
      Bottom</guilabel>. They may look similar to the <guilabel>X Position
      (From Left)</guilabel> and <guilabel>Y Position (From Top)</guilabel>
      but there is a major difference: the Crop Origin Nudge settings apply to
      the Extra Image <emphasis role="bold">before</emphasis> it is resized.
      While the Position options let you move the resized image around the
      template so it can fit your composition with the Base Image, the Crop
      Origin Nudge options allow you to scroll the original image around so
      that the resize and crop can focus on a different region of the image.
      Moreover, each Crop Origin Nudge option will have no effect if that
      would cause the image to go outside the template area, or if the width /
      height of the image is smaller than the respective template
      dimension.</para>

      <para>You can best understand these options editing the Overlay
      template, using the Lindsey (very tall) and Spiske (very wide) images in
      the Template Preview.</para>

      <bridgehead>Image effects</bridgehead>

      <para>You can optionally apply the following image effects:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Grayscale. Removes the colour from the image without affecting
          its contrast and brightness. It can be from 0 (no effect) to 100
          (all colour removed). You can use intermediate values to mute
          colours towards a neutral black and white palette without removing
          all colour.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Sepia. Applies a sepia colour filter.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Opacity. Adjust the opacity of the image, from 0 (fully
          transparent) to 100 (fully opaque). Do note that semi-transparent
          areas of the image are kept at their current alpha (transparency)
          value at 100, and are made more transparent for lower values. This
          may result in some semi-transparent areas becoming fully transparent
          as you are decreasing this value.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="template-text">
      <title>Text</title>

      <para>The final, and topmost, layer of an OpenGraph image template in
      SocialMagick is for (optional) text.</para>

      <para>If you do not want any text at all, set the <guilabel>Overlay
      Text</guilabel> option to No. Do note that this cannot be overridden in
      categories, content items, and menu items. It completely disables text
      overlays with this template.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The Template does not allow you to select a source for the text.
        This is always set at the category, content item, or menu item level.
        The template only tells SocialMagick whether and how to render overlay
        text. It does not tell it what to text to render. This is quite
        different than the Extra Image tab which defines both the source, and
        the rendering options.</para>
      </note>

      <bridgehead>Fonts and Colours</bridgehead>

      <para>The <guilabel>Font For Text</guilabel> lets you select a
      <trademark class="registered">TrueType</trademark> (<code>.ttf</code>)
      font file to use for rendering the text. SocialMagick comes with two
      font files for the Open Sans Bold and Open Sans Bold Italic typefaces.
      If you would like to use different fonts, upload the corresponding
      TrueType font files into the
      <code>plugins/system/socialmagick/fonts</code> directory of your site.
      Kindly note that you are solely responsible for adhering to the license
      of the font you are using. Some fonts may be free for use on the web,
      but not for use in images – even if automatically generated ones. The
      Open Sans font is a thoroughly Open Source font, without any
      restrictions.</para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Font Size (in points)</guilabel> lets you select how
      big the text will be. We are using points, not pixel, sizes because they
      are the most common font size metric in text and graphics processing
      software. If you want to work out the font size in pixels, it's 1.33
      pixels to a point and 0.75 points to a pixel. We recommend font sizes
      between 40 to 70 points as your image will be scaled down 2–3 times when
      displayed. Text smaller than that would be unreadable in many practical
      use cases.</para>

      <note>
        <para>There are 72 points to an inch. Graphics are rendered by
        browsers at an average density of 96 pixels per inch. Therefore one
        point is 1.33 pixels. Conversely, that's 0.75 points per pixel. A 16
        pixel text size (the default used by most browsers) is 12pt.</para>
      </note>

      <para>The <guilabel>Text Colour</guilabel> and
      <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel> control the colour (fill) of the text. You
      may want to use an Opacity lower than 100 –therefore, semi-transparent
      text– for artistic effect. This works best with large font sizes
      rendered over a large area of the image.</para>

      <para>Sometimes it may be hard to make out the text against a background
      that's either busy, or a similar luminosity to the text. This is a
      long-understood problem; it affected movie and television subtitles,
      too! The solution is to have a contrasting contour surrounding and
      following the letter shapes to better isolate them from the background.
      This is called a stroke. You can use the <guilabel>Text Stroke
      Colour</guilabel> and <guilabel>Text Stroke Width</guilabel> to select
      the colour of the stroke, and how wide it will be <emphasis>in
      pixels</emphasis>. If you do not want a text stroke set the
      <guilabel>Text Stroke Width</guilabel> to 0. Please note that if you set
      an <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel> less than 100 for the text colour, the
      text stroke will also have the same opacity. This is intentional. The
      text is rendered with the stroke, and the opacity is applied to the
      whole overlay text including the stroke.</para>

      <bridgehead>Text positioning</bridgehead>

      <para>SocialMagick renders text inside a text box. The size (width and
      height) of this text box is given in the <guilabel>Maximum Text Height
      (px)</guilabel> and <guilabel>Maximum Text Width (px)</guilabel>
      options.</para>

      <para>The positioning of the text box on the horizontal and vertical
      axis can either be centered, or positioned exactly as a number of pixels
      measured from the edge of the image.</para>

      <para>Enabling <guilabel>Centre text vertically?</guilabel> (default)
      will position the text box on the vertical axis so that its centre point
      is halfway between the top and bottom edge of the image. Use the
      <guilabel>Nudge Vertically from Centre (px)</guilabel> option to move
      the text box vertically towards the bottom (positive numbers) or the top
      (negative numbers) of the image.</para>

      <para>Disabling <guilabel>Centre text vertically?</guilabel> will
      position the text box on the vertical axis so that its top edge
      coincides with the image's top edge. Use the <guilabel>Pixels from the
      Top</guilabel> option to move the text box towards the bottom of the
      image.</para>

      <para>Enabling <guilabel>Centre text horizontally?</guilabel> (default)
      will position the text box on the horizontal axis so that its centre
      point is halfway between the left and right edge of the image. Use the
      <guilabel>Nudge Horizontally from Centre (px)</guilabel> option to move
      the text box horizontally towards the right (positive numbers) or the
      left (negative numbers) of the image.</para>

      <para>Disabling <guilabel>Centre text horizontally?</guilabel> will
      position the text box on the horizontal axis so that its left edge
      coincides with the image's left edge. Use the <guilabel>Pixels from the
      Left</guilabel> option to move the text box towards the right of the
      image.</para>

      <bridgehead>Text fit and truncation</bridgehead>

      <para>SocialMagick uses a text rendering concept which is a lot like how
      a browser would render text in a block container with the CSS style
      <code>overflow: hidden; text-overflow: ellipsis;</code>.</para>

      <para>Here's how it works. The text is broken down into word-like pieces
      by finding spaces (ASCII 32) in the text. These word-like pieces are
      distributed into "lines" so that each line contains as many (but at
      least one!) word-like pieces keeping its length under the Maximum Text
      Width. Then, the algorithm tries to see how many of these "lines" fit
      fully within the Maximum Text Height and throws away the rest. If not
      all word-like pieces were used, it will try to add ellipsis
      (<code>…</code>) after the last word-like piece of the last line it will
      render. If that makes the line exceed the Maximum Text Width it will
      delete the last word-like piece of the last line, replacing it with
      ellipsis.</para>

      <para>The following edge cases cannot be handled:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If your vertical or horizontal height are small enough that
          not even one word-like part can be rendered fully within the
          allocated text space, no text will be rendered. This is a deliberate
          choice. In any other case, you'd end up with clipped, unreadable
          text.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Some languages, especially Asian ones, do not use spaces
          (ASCII 32) to separate words. Therefore, the entire text may end up
          being considered one long word-like piece. Likewise, if your words
          are separated by punctuation other than regular spaces –such as
          dashes, underscores, points, etc– these will be considered a single
          word-like piece (e.g. <code>do-not-disturb</code> is considered
          <emphasis>one</emphasis> word-like piece). This may result in your
          entire text being considered as a few very long word-like pieces
          which exceed the Maximum Text Width and are clipped as a result.
          Moreover, if you have more than one of these pieces you may end up
          in a situation where the only text rendered is the ellipsis or (for
          small enough text box sizes and big enough font sizes) seemingly
          nothing at all.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Quotes, parentheses, braces, and other punctuation are
          consider as part of a word-like piece. This may result in rendered
          text such as <code>He said: “enough…</code> which is grammatically
          incorrect. Do note that browsers rendering text with hidden overflow
          also suffer from the same problem. In fact, there is no good way to
          automatically handle this use case without rewriting the
          text.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In most cases, the default behaviour is fine. If you hit the
      aforementioned edge cases it is best to override the rendered text at
      the content or menu item level with something that reads and displays
      well.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="socialmagick-plugins">
    <title>Integration Plugins</title>

    <para>SocialMagick generates OpenGraph data and images for all pages of
    your site. To do that it needs to somehow retrieve the text to be used for
    the OpenGraph image template (if you select to use a text overlay), and
    the image to be used as the Extra Image for the OpenGraph image template.
    Moreover, it needs to have different kinds of integration code to display
    the OpenGraph options tab when editing categories, content items, and menu
    items.</para>

    <para>While older versions of SocialMagick had these integrations
    hardcoded, SocialMagick 3 and later versions use integration plugins.
    These are standard Joomla plugins in the <code>socialmagick</code>
    group.</para>

    <section xml:id="socialmagick-articles">
      <title>SocialMagick – Articles</title>

      <para>This plugin allows SocialMagick to integrate with Joomla articles.
      You must have this plugin enabled for this integration to
      function.</para>

      <para>The plugin is responsible for rendering the OpenGraph tab when you
      are editing a Joomla article.</para>

      <para>When your frontend page is displaying a Joomla article, this
      plugin makes the following information available to SocialMagick:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The article title can be used as the OpenGraph image template
          text when you enable <guilabel>Use Content Title</guilabel>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The article's Intro Image and Full Text Image can be used as
          the Extra Image in the OpenGraph image template.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A Joomla custom Field can be used as the Extra Image in the
          OpenGraph image template.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <important>
        <para>The <guilabel>Access</guilabel> for this plugin <emphasis
        role="bold">MUST</emphasis> always be set to
        <guilabel>Public</guilabel>. See the <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel> tab
        for options limiting access to the OpenGraph tab to specific user
        groups.</para>
      </important>

      <para>The configuration options in the <guilabel>Plugin</guilabel> tab
      are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Extra Image Source</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The default Extra Image source for Joomla articles. This can
            be overridden at the category, article, and menu item level. The
            available options are:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><option>None</option>. No Extra Image will be
                used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><option>Intro Image</option>. The article's Intro Image
                will be used, if present. Otherwise, no Extra Image will be
                used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><option>Full Article Image</option>. The article's Full
                Article Image will be used, if present. Otherwise, no Extra
                Image will be used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><option>Custom Field</option>. The image provided by the
                custom field whose name is set up below will be used, if
                present. Otherwise, no Extra Image will be used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><option>Full Article, or Intro Image</option>. The
                article's Full Article Image will be used, if present. If it's
                not present, the article's Intro Image will be used. If
                neither image is present, no Extra Image will be used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><option>Intro, or Full Article image</option>. The
                article's Intro Image will be used, if present. If it's not
                present, the article's Full Article will be used. If neither
                image is present, no Extra Image will be used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><option>Custom Field, Full Article, or Intro
                Image</option>. The image provided by the custom field whose
                name is set up below will be used, if present. If there is no
                custom image field, or it's empty, the article's Full Article
                Image will be used, if present. If it's not present, the
                article's Intro Image will be used. If none of these images is
                present, no Extra Image will be used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><option>Custom Field, Intro, or Full Article
                Image</option>. The image provided by the custom field whose
                name is set up below will be used, if present. If there is no
                custom image field, or it's empty, the article's Intro Image
                will be used, if present. If it's not present, the article's
                Full Article Image will be used. If none of these images is
                present, no Extra Image will be used.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Extra Image Field Name</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <guilabel>Name</guilabel> of the Joomla Field of the
            article which has the Extra Image to use in the OpenGraph image
            template. This must be a Media or Text field, or an equivalent
            third party field type. The contents of the field <emphasis
            role="bold">MUST</emphasis> be the absolute or relative filesystem
            path to an image hosted on your web server. You cannot use URLs,
            or images hosted externally to your site such as a CDN, Amazon S3,
            Dropbox, etc.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Use Article Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tells SocialMagick to use the article's title as the text
            overlay source. If disabled, the <guilabel>Use Content
            Title</guilabel> option will have no effect by default.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Use Article Description</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tells SocialMagick to use the article's Meta Description as
            the OpenGraph description. You can override this in categories,
            articles, and menu items. If this is disabled, SocialMagick will
            instead use the Meta Description set up in the currently used menu
            item. Please note that in if you have a Category List or Category
            Blog menu item and click on an article this category view menu
            item will be used by Joomla <emphasis>even if you have a different
            menu item for the specific article you clicked on</emphasis>. This
            is a deliberate choice in Joomla; it's what allows Modules to be
            so flexible and powerful.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel> tab allows you to specify who
      for and where the OpenGraph tab will be visible when editing a Joomla
      article.</para>

      <note>
        <para>All users who belong to the Super User group are NOT limited by
        the options in this tab. Super User accounts can always see the
        OpenGraph tab. The reason is that Super Users in Joomla have, by
        definition, all privileges explicitly Allowed to them, i.e. the should
        and can do anything and everything on the site.</para>
      </note>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Allow Frontend Editing of OpenGraph Settings</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Should the OpenGraph settings tab show up when editing an
            article in the frontend of the site? Super Users are not limited
            by this setting.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Limit OpenGraph Settings To Users Of These Groups</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If this is empty, any user who can edit an article will see
            the OpenGraph tab. Otherwise, only users belonging to one or more
            of the groups specified here –or one of their child groups– will
            be see that tab. Super Users are not limited by this
            setting.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="socialmagick-categories">
      <title>SocialMagick – Categories</title>

      <para>This plugin allows SocialMagick to integrate with Joomla article
      categories. You must have this plugin enabled for this integration to
      function.</para>

      <important>
        <para>This integration plugin only applies to <emphasis
        role="bold">article</emphasis> categories. It does not apply to
        categories used by other core and third party components such as
        Banners, Contacts, News Feeds etc.</para>
      </important>

      <para>The plugin is responsible for rendering the OpenGraph tab when you
      are editing a Joomla article category.</para>

      <para>When your frontend page is displaying a Joomla category (e.g. any
      of the default category blog or category list view options), this plugin
      makes the following information available to SocialMagick:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The category title can be used as the OpenGraph image template
          text when you enable <guilabel>Use Content Title</guilabel>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The category's Image can be used as the Extra Image in the
          OpenGraph image template.</para>

          <note>
            <para>The Template shows the options Full Article Image and Intro
            Image. <emphasis>Either</emphasis> of these settings returns the
            category Image for category items.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A Joomla custom Field can be used as the Extra Image in the
          OpenGraph image template.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The configuration options in the <guilabel>Plugin</guilabel> tab
      are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Extra Image Source</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The default Extra Image source for Joomla article categoris.
            This can be overridden at the category, and menu item level. The
            available options are:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><option>None</option>. No Extra Image will be
                used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><option>Category</option>. The article category's Image
                will be used, if present. Otherwise, no Extra Image will be
                used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><option>Custom Field</option>. The image provided by the
                category custom field whose name is set up below will be used,
                if present. Otherwise, no Extra Image will be used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><option>Custom Field, or Category</option>. The image
                provided by the custom field whose name is set up below will
                be used, if present. If there is no custom image field, or
                it's empty, the article category's image will be used, if
                present. If it's not present, no Extra Image will be
                used.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Extra Image Field Name</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <guilabel>Name</guilabel> of the Joomla Field of the
            article category which has the Extra Image to use in the OpenGraph
            image template. This must be a Media or Text field, or an
            equivalent third party field type. The contents of the field
            <emphasis role="bold">MUST</emphasis> be the absolute or relative
            filesystem path to an image hosted on your web server. You cannot
            use URLs, or images hosted externally to your site such as a CDN,
            Amazon S3, Dropbox, etc.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Use Category Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tells SocialMagick to use the article category's title as
            the text overlay source. If disabled, the <guilabel>Use Content
            Title</guilabel> option will have no effect by default.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Use Category Description</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tells SocialMagick to use the category's Meta Description as
            the OpenGraph description. You can override this in categories and
            menu items. If this is disabled, SocialMagick will instead use the
            Meta Description set up in the currently used menu item.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel> tab allows you to specify who
      for and where the OpenGraph tab will be visible when editing a Joomla
      article category.</para>

      <note>
        <para>All users who belong to the Super User group are NOT limited by
        the options in this tab. Super User accounts can always see the
        OpenGraph tab. The reason is that Super Users in Joomla have, by
        definition, all privileges explicitly Allowed to them, i.e. the should
        and can do anything and everything on the site.</para>
      </note>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Allow Frontend Editing of OpenGraph Settings</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Should the OpenGraph settings tab show up when editing an
            article category in the frontend of the site?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Limit OpenGraph Settings To Users Of These Groups</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If this is empty, any user who can edit an article category
            will see the OpenGraph tab. Otherwise, only users belonging to one
            or more of the groups specified here –or one of their child
            groups– will be see that tab.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="socialmagick-menus">
      <title>SocialMagick – Menu Items</title>

      <para>This integration plugin must be enabled for SocialMagick to be
      able to show OpenGraph tabs in menu items, and use these settings to
      override component, category, and content item OpenGraph
      parameters.</para>

      <para>If you disable this integration plugin you can expect SocialMagick
      to behave in ways that you will perceive as wrong, weird, or outright
      broken.</para>

      <para>This is a plugin because there are very few, very specific use
      cases which warrant this kind of weird behaviour. If you are unsure if
      that applies to you, chances are it does not. It's one of those things
      that you know when you need it, and shouldn't touch if you don't
      absolutely need to do something really weird...</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="in-depth-information">
    <title>In-depth information</title>

    <section xml:id="component-options">
      <title>Component options</title>

      <para>The SocialMagic component includes a number of
      <guilabel>Options</guilabel> which control its default behaviour. The
      options under the <guilabel>Basic</guilabel> and <guilabel>OpenGraph
      Tags</guilabel> tabs can be overridden at the category, content item,
      and menu item level.</para>

      <para><guilabel>Basic</guilabel></para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Generate OpenGraph Images By Default</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>OpenGraph images will be generated for all pages on your
            site unless explicitly configured not to, for example at the menu
            or article level. When disabled, you will have to explicitly
            configure menu items, articles, etc to generate OpenGraph
            images.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Default Template</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The OpenGraph image generation template to use. You have to
            save the plugin before selecting a template you just created or
            renamed. This option can be overridden in a menu item, category or
            article.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para><guilabel>OpenGraph Tags</guilabel></para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Add OpenGraph Property Declaration</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>SocialMagick will add the OpenGraph namespace declaration to
            the <code>&lt;html&gt;</code> element of your site's HTML output.
            Leave enabled unless you have a custom template or a third party
            extension which does that for you. Even in this case it is safe to
            leave this option enabled; SocialMagick will check if the
            namespace declaration is present to avoid creating a duplicate
            definition.</para>

            <important>
              <para>If the OpenGraph namespace declaration is missing most
              third party sites and services will NOT be able to read the
              OpenGraph data of your site, even if this data is present in the
              <code>&lt;head&gt;</code> section of the HTML page.</para>
            </important>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>OpenGraph Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tells SocialMagic which text to use when setting the
            <code>og:title</code> property in the HTML document. This
            communicates the title of the current page to social media sites.
            Setting this to No disables this feature.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>OpenGraph Description</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tells SocialMagic which text to use when setting the
            <code>og:description</code> property in the HTML document. This
            communicates the summary (description) of the current page to
            social media sites. Setting this to No disables this
            feature.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>OpenGraph URL</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tells SocialMagic whether to set the <code>og:url</code>
            property in the HTML document. This communicates the URL of the
            current page to social media sites. This property is largely
            redundant for Joomla! sites. It only serves to satisfy OpenGraph
            validators which might complain if it's missing.</para>

            <tip>
              <para>If you are not sure whether you need the OpenGraph URL or
              not, it's best to enable it. Having it when the consumer site /
              application doesn't need it doesn't hurt. Not having it when
              it's needed, though, may lead to undesired display of the links
              you share.</para>
            </tip>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>OpenGraph Site Name</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tells SocialMagic whether to set the
            <code>og:site_name</code> property in the HTML document. This
            communicates the name of the site to social media sites.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>X (formerly Twitter) Card type</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set the sharing card type on X (formerly Twitter). Summary
            shows the page title, description and a small thumbnail. Summary
            with Large Image is similar to Summary but uses a larger,
            prominent version of your page's OpenGraph image. If you use None
            X will show its default preview which may include a preview image.
            Using either card type requires that your page has an og:image
            property set either by this plugin or by a third party extension,
            otherwise it has no effect.</para>

            <para>You can use this option even if you don't care about, plan
            to use, or support X; its properties are read by other social
            media sites and applications as a hint on how to best display a
            link preview.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>X Site Handle</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The X handle used by your site, including the @ sign in
            front.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>X Creator Handle</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The default X handle which will be attributed as the content
            creator. Generally recommended to only set this in articles, not
            in the component Options.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Facebook App ID</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If your site is using a Facebook app, e.g. for social login,
            you are recommended to enter the Facebook App ID here so that
            Facebook can attribute the links of your site to that Facebook
            app. If you have no idea what this is you can safely omit
            it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para><guilabel>Advanced</guilabel></para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Image Type</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The image file type for generated OpenGraph images. PNG and
            JPG are universally supported. PNG generates massive files which
            preserve transparency, JPG (default) generates fairly small files
            with some visual artifacts and does not support transparency. WebP
            produces the smallest files with minimal visual artifacts and does
            support transparency, but some niche services and (usually older
            versions of) third party software may not be able to display WebP
            files. If you know your links won't be shared in any niche
            software / service (or don't care about them), we recommend
            switching this option to WebP for best quality and size.</para>

            <para>As of the writing of this documentation (September 2025) all
            major third party services and applications support WebP, with a
            question about whether Discord supports lossless WebP (what you
            get with a quality setting of 90 or higher).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Image Quality</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Controls the quality of the generated image by adjusting the
            compression level.</para>

            <para>0 is the worst image quality, at the best compression rate
            and smallest image size, but is rarely usable. 100 is the best
            image quality, using no compression and the highest image size.
            The exact semantics of this option depend on the image format you
            chose to use.</para>

            <para>PNG: This file format only has 10 <emphasis
            role="bold">lossless</emphasis> compression levels ranging from 0
            (uncompressed) to 9 (maximum compression). Lossless means that
            there is no change in image quality at all, only a small impact on
            file size. SocialMagick maps image quality 0-10 to PNG compression
            level 9, 11-20 to PNG compression level 8, ..., 81-90 to PNG
            compression level 1, and 91-100 to PNG compression level 0. We
            recommend using image quality 0 (maximum compression) on most
            servers. On slow servers, use image quality 60 (compression level
            4).</para>

            <warning>
              <para>PNG compression depends heavily on the capabilities of the
              PHP graphics handling library and the content of the image. Busy
              images will see practically no size change across the entire
              range of Image Quality.</para>
            </warning>

            <para>JPG: The JPG format uses a lossy compression algorithm.
            Image Quality levels below 30 are very strongly NOT recommended
            because the visual artifacts make them unusable. Moreover, an
            Image Quality beyond 85 makes the file significantly larger
            without any perceived improvement in quality. We recommend an
            image quality of 60 to 75. The default value (75) is the one
            recommended by the JPG standard.</para>

            <para>WebP: Image Quality levels 0 to 89 use lossy compression
            which can affect image quality. Image quality 90 to 100 uses
            lossless compression which will result in fairly small files with
            no loss of image quality whatsoever. The default image quality
            (75) is a good balance between quality and file size. You can get
            significantly better quality at a small increase in file size
            using quality level 100, but some sites may not be able to display
            your OpenGraph image.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Regenerate Images On Every Page Load (Development Mode)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>By default, SocialMagick only regenerates an OpenGraph image
            for a specific page when it detects that the text, Extra Image,
            template, or template settings have changed since the last time it
            generated an image for that page.</para>

            <para>If you are troubleshooting and need to override this image
            caching behaviour, you need to enable this option. Please note
            that this has a very high impact on your site's performance as
            SocialMagick will try to generate images on every page
            load!</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Debug Text Layout</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Enables the <link linkend="debug-text-layout">Debug Text
            Layout</link> feature. This feature renders the text box and
            overlay text lines bounding boxes on the generated OpenGraph
            image. You should only enable that on development sites, always
            together with the <guilabel>Regenerate Images On Every Page Load
            (Development Mode) </guilabel> option.</para>

            <para>Instead of using this option, we strongly recommend using
            the Template Preview feature when editing a template, enabling the
            Debug Text Layout checkbox for the Template Preview. Doing so will
            NOT affect your generated OpenGraph images and does not run the
            risk of a third party site or application showing and caching an
            OpenGraph image with the Debug Text Layout markings on it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Frontend Preview Button</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>SocialMagick will display a preview floating on pages it has
            generated an OpenGraph image. Clicking on it allows you to preview
            the OpenGraph image and properties of the page without having to
            view source, or use a third party site / tool. You can choose
            which Joomla User Groups will see this button below. See <link
            linkend="frontend-preview">Frontend Preview</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Frontend Preview Access Level</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Choose the Joomla Access Level which will see the Frontend
            Preview Button. The default value is <option>Special</option>,
            allowing only Administrator and Super User accounts to see the
            button.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>PHP Image Handling Extensions</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Choose which PHP extension to use to generate OpenGraph
            images. Use <option>Auto-detect</option> unless our support
            explicitly asks you to do otherwise. <option>ImageMagick</option>
            uses the <code>imagick</code> PHP extension (faster, you may have
            to ask your host to install or enable). <option>GD</option> uses
            the PHP <code>gd</code> extension (slower, installed on most
            servers). If your selected library is not available no images will
            be generated. <option>Auto-detect</option> uses ImageMagick if
            available, falls back to GD if not.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="debug-text-layout">
      <title>Debug text layout</title>

      <para>When you are designing a template one of the hardest concept to
      wrap your head around is how text is rendered. That's because of the
      number of variables involved: font, font size, the size of the text box,
      its positioning on the page, aligning the text, and how the text gets
      cut off when it overflows.</para>

      <para>The best way to understand it is to visualise the position and
      size of the text box itself, and the text in it. Maybe play around with
      different text strings, fonts, and font sizes. This is what the Debug
      Text Layout does. It visualises the text box and the rendered text so
      you can figure out how to best set up your template's overlay
      text.</para>

      <important>
        <para>Please note that each PHP graphics library –ImageMagick
        (<code>imagick</code>) and GD (<code>gd</code>)– render the same text
        slightly differently. This comes down to the different font rendering
        mechanism each library uses.</para>

        <para>When you are developing on a development or staging server
        please make sure that you use the same library you will be using on
        your live site.</para>
      </important>

      <para><bridgehead>ImageMagick</bridgehead></para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/debugtext-imagick.png" scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>When you enable Debug Text Layout using ImageMagick you see the
      text box rendered as a translucent yellow box with a thin solid purple
      border. The position of the text box depends on the following template
      settings:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Centre text vertically</guilabel>. Whether the text
          box is vertically anchored to the middle of the image (Yes) or to
          the top side of the image (No).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Nudge Vertically from Centre (px)</guilabel> /
          <guilabel>Pixels from the Top</guilabel>. How many pixels to the
          bottom (positive numbers) or top (negative numbers) the text box
          will move vertically from its anchor position.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Centre text horizontally</guilabel>. Whether the
          text box is horizontally anchored to the middle of the image (Yes)
          or to the left hand side of the image (No).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Nudge Horizontally from Centre (px)</guilabel> /
          <guilabel>Pixels from Left Edge</guilabel>. How many pixels to the
          right (positive numbers) or left (negative numbers) the text box
          will move horizontally from its anchor position.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The size of the text box depends on the following template
      settings:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Maximum Text Width (px)</guilabel>. The width
          (horizontal size) of the text box.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Maximum Text Height (px)</guilabel>. The height
          (vertical size) of the text box.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>ImageMagick renders all text lines as a single text label
      regardless of the number of actual text lines. You can see the outline
      of the rendered text label as a thin dashed purple border.</para>

      <para>The positioning of the text label within the text box is
      automatic: it is always placed in the centre of the text box.</para>

      <para>The alignment of the text within the text label (Left, Centre, or
      Right) is determined by the Text Align template option.</para>

      <bridgehead>GD</bridgehead>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/debugtext-gd.png" scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>When you enable Debug Text Layout using GD you see the text box
      rendered as a translucent yellow box. Unlike when using the ImageMagick
      library, you will also see that it extends 50 pixels to all sides,
      rendered as a translucent pink background with a thin solid purple
      border. This is the text gutter which is required by GD to render text
      (if the text to be rendered is exactly the same size as the text box,
      you get strange artifacts or crashes). Do note that the gutter is added
      automatically. Your template settings only affect the size and
      positioning of the text box itself.</para>

      <note>
        <para>In very rare cases (especially decorative fonts with character
        elements extending beyond the character's render cell) you may see
        parts of the font rendered inside the gutter area. In those rare cases
        we strongly recommend using a different font, or switching to
        ImageMagick which handles those cases more gracefully.</para>

        <para>We also want to note that GD tends to render the text a bit
        smaller and “rougher” than ImageMagick. Its only benefit is that it's
        available and enabled on virtually every server which runs PHP,
        whereas ImageMagick usually needs to be explicitly enabled by you, or
        your systems administrator.</para>
      </note>

      <para>The position of the text box (yellow background) depends on the
      following template settings:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Centre text vertically</guilabel>. Whether the text
          box is vertically anchored to the middle of the image (Yes) or to
          the top side of the image (No).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Nudge Vertically from Centre (px)</guilabel> /
          <guilabel>Pixels from the Top</guilabel>. How many pixels to the
          bottom (positive numbers) or top (negative numbers) the text box
          will move vertically from its anchor position.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Centre text horizontally</guilabel>. Whether the
          text box is horizontally anchored to the middle of the image (Yes)
          or to the left hand side of the image (No).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Nudge Horizontally from Centre (px)</guilabel> /
          <guilabel>Pixels from Left Edge</guilabel>. How many pixels to the
          right (positive numbers) or left (negative numbers) the text box
          will move horizontally from its anchor position.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The size of the text box (yellow background) depends on the
      following template settings:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Maximum Text Width (px)</guilabel>. The width
          (horizontal size) of the text box.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Maximum Text Height (px)</guilabel>. The height
          (vertical size) of the text box.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>GD renders each text line as an individual text label. You can see
      the outline of each line's text label as a thin dashed purple
      border.</para>

      <para>The positioning of the text labels within the text box is
      automatic: they are always placed so that the entire text is vertically
      and horizontally centred inside the text box. The vertical distance
      between the text labels of each line cannot be changed; it is set by the
      font itself (it's the line height which is calculated by GD based on the
      font characters' render cell height).</para>

      <para>The alignment of the text within the text label (Left, Centre, or
      Right) is determined by the Text Align template option.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="frontend-preview">
      <title>Frontend preview</title>

      <para>SocialMagick works in a generally invisible way, creating
      OpenGraph images and setting up OpenGraph data for your site's pages.
      But how do you know that the data it creates and the images it creates
      is what you were aiming for? Normally, that would require viewing the
      page's source to inspect the meta tags in the HTML head. If you want to
      see the OpenGraph image you have to find the OpenGraph image tag, get
      the image URL from it, and open it in another browser tab. That's a lot
      of work.</para>

      <para>Instead, you can enabled the Frontend Preview option in the
      component's <guibutton>Options</guibutton> page.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>You can also limit which <emphasis role="bold">user
        groups</emphasis> can see this button. You may want, for example, to
        only allow Manager, Administrator, and Super User accounts to see this
        button in the frontend as it makes no sense for regular users to see
        it. Or, you may have a development or staging site where you want to
        enable this button for everyone, even guests, because you're working
        on a site which does not allow frontend user login. It's up to
        you!</para>
      </tip>

      <para>This shows a button towards the bottom right of the screen for
      every page on your site. It looks like this:</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/frontend-preview-btn.png" scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Clicking on this button opens up the OpenGraph Preview modal
      window, which looks like this:</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/frontend-preview.png" scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The top half of the modal window shows you how third parties will
      display a link to this page of your site including the OpenGraph image
      (if any), the domain name, the OpenGraph title, and the OpenGraph
      description. The template used is very similar to how Facebook displays
      links. Other sites and applications may use a slightly different
      arrangement of the same elements.</para>

      <para>The bottom half of the modal window shows you the individual
      OpenGraph properties on the page:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Image. A link to the OpenGraph image. Click on it to open the
          image in a new tab.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>URL. The URL to your page. This is the URL reported by Joomla
          and <emphasis>should</emphasis> be the URL you see in your browser
          in most cases. Please note that the URL will never include the page
          fragment (<code>#something</code>), as this information is not
          communicated by the browser to the server,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Title. The OpenGraph title. It could be the same as the Joomla
          browser title (default), the content item title, or custom text you
          have entered depending on what kind of content you are displaying,
          the availability of an integration plugin for it, and your
          preferences.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Description. It could be the same as the Joomla meta
          description for the menu item, the content's meta description, or
          custom text you have entered depending on what kind of content you
          are displaying, the availability of an integration plugin for it,
          and your preferences.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="managing-php-image-exts">
      <title>Managing the PHP image extensions</title>

      <para>SocialMagick works by manipulating image data to generate
      OpenGraph images. PHP is a language which is primarily made to
      manipulate text and numbers. For PHP to manipulate image data it needs
      an extension designed for that installed and enabled.</para>

      <para>The two extensions PHP can use to manipulate image date are
      <code>imagick</code> and <code>gd</code>.</para>

      <para>The <code>gd</code> extension integrates the venerable GD library
      with PHP. This is one of the oldest continuously developed image data
      manipulation libraries, first created in 1987. However, it is also the
      most limited of the two. It's slower. It does not support colour
      profiles, leading to images rendered with colors which appear to be
      either washed out or with too much contrast compared to what your
      browser renders, especially when your image source is digital photos. It
      does not support SVG files; it can only manage raster (bitmap) files. It
      also produces much more pronounced compression artifacts, while
      generating larger files.</para>

      <para>The <code>imagick</code> extension integrates the ImageMagick
      library with PHP. ImageMagick is a slightly newer library, starting
      development in 1990. It is fast. It supports colour profiles, resulting
      in colour-accurate results. It supports SVG files just fine; it
      automatically converts them to a bitmap format <emphasis>using the image
      size encoded in the SVG file</emphasis>. It produces smaller files, with
      less visible compression artifacts.</para>

      <para>In this section you will find out how to tell which extension you
      have enabled, and how you can get <code>imagick</code> enabled if you
      currently have neither extension enabled.</para>

      <section xml:id="which-ext-is-installed">
        <title>Which extension do I have installed?</title>

        <para>It is very important for you to remember that there is not one
        PHP installation or configuration on your server.</para>

        <para>Your host may have multiple PHP versions made available to you.
        It is possible to have a different PHP version enabled for the
        <uri>administrator</uri> backend of your site than you have in your
        frontend. For this reason, you are going to check the PHP version, and
        its configuration, on both the frontend and the backend of the site.
        In both cases, we're going to get the detailed PHP information – what
        to look for is explained further below.</para>

        <bridgehead>The backend of your site</bridgehead>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Log into your site's <uri>administrator</uri> as a Super
            User.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the sidebar, go to <guimenu>System</guimenu>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Under the <guilabel>Information</guilabel> heading click on
            <guilabel>System Information</guilabel>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <guilabel>PHP Information</guilabel>
            tab.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>If you have <code>imagick</code> installed and enabled you will
        see an <guilabel>imagick</guilabel> section like the following
        screenshot.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/backend-phpinfo.jpg" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>Likewise, if you have <code>gd</code> installed and enabled you
        will see a <guilabel>gd</guilabel> section like the following
        screenshot.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/backend-phpinfo-gd.jpg" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <bridgehead>The frontend of your site.</bridgehead>

        <para>Create a new file on your computer named
        <filename>phpinfo.php</filename>. Edit it with a plain text editor
        such as Notepad and set its contents to:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;?php phpinfo();</programlisting>

        <para>Upload it to your site's root, next to Joomla's
        <filename>index.php</filename> file. You can use your hosting control
        panel's file manager, FTP, SFTP, or whichever option you
        prefer.</para>

        <note>
          <para>If you are using Admin Tools Professional's .htaccess Maker
          you will have to go to your site's backend, Components, Admin Tools
          for Joomla, .htaccess Maker and add a new row under <guilabel>Allow
          direct access to these files</guilabel>. Set its value to
          <filename>phpinfo.php</filename> and click on <guibutton>Save and
          create .htaccess</guibutton>.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Now visit the <uri>/phpinfo.php</uri> URL of your site. For
        example, if your site lives in <uri>https://www.example.com</uri> you
        need to visit <uri>https://www.example.com/phpinfo.php</uri>.
        Likewise, if your site lives in <uri>http://localhost/mysite</uri> you
        need to visit <uri>http://localhost/mysite/phpinfo.php</uri>.</para>

        <para>Look for the same <code>imagick</code> or <code>gd</code>
        sections.</para>

        <bridgehead>When you need to do something</bridgehead>

        <para>You need to do something in any of the following cases:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>There is no image extension in either the backend or the
            frontend.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The image extension available in the backend and frontend
            are different.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A different PHP version is listed at the very top of the
            backend and frontend pages.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>In those cases, please look at the next section.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="enable-imagemagick">
        <title>Enabling ImageMagick</title>

        <para>Before you begin, make sure that your backend and frontend use
        the same PHP version. This is <emphasis>very important</emphasis>!
        Different versions of PHP will be using different versions of the
        <code>imagick</code> extension and, possibly, the ImageMagick library
        itself. This discrepancy can very likely mean that what you see in the
        template preview in the backend of your site IS NOT what you get in
        the frontend where it matters the most. Having the same PHP version
        throughout your site is an excellent idea anyway, as it reduces this
        kind of weird issues which will catch you off-guard – not just in our
        extension, but other third party extensions and even Joomla itself. If
        you're not sure how to do that, or even check for it, do ask your
        host.</para>

        <para>Once you have confirmed that you are using the same PHP version
        throughout your site, you can proceed to configuring PHP to enable the
        <code>imagick</code> extension.</para>

        <bridgehead>I don't want to do any of this by myself!</bridgehead>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">YOU DON'T HAVE TO</emphasis>!</para>

        <para>Most people want to manage a site, not a server. That's probably
        why you use a commercial host. Ask your host to enable the
        <code>imagick</code> PHP extension on your site. That's it!</para>

        <para>As for why this page exists, the reason is simple: there are
        people who want to learn how to do basic server management themselves
        because it tends to be faster. This page is here to help them, not
        force you to do something you don't want to.</para>

        <para><bridgehead>On commercial hosting</bridgehead></para>

        <para>Most commercial hosts have a place where you can change your PHP
        configuration, and select the extensions which are enabled on your
        site.</para>

        <para>For example, most cPanel hosts have a Select PHP Version option.
        In it, you just need to check the <code>imagick</code> option. The
        screenshot below is from the cPanel hosting control panel, as
        configured by the hosting company Rochen.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cpanel_imagick.png" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>Other hosting companies may use a slightly different method. If
        unsure, please ask your host.</para>

        <para><bridgehead>Local hosting (MAMP, XAMPP, WAMPServer,
        etc)</bridgehead></para>

        <para>Local server packages such as MAMP, XAMP, WAMPServer etc
        typically do not come with the <code>imagick</code> extension
        preinstalled. You will need to either copy its DLL files (Windows), or
        compile it (macOS, Linux).</para>

        <para>We recommend asking ChatGPT or a similar AI assistant a question
        such as "how do I install and enable the PHP imagick extension on MAMP
        7.2.0 running under macOS Tahoe". Remember to replace the hosting
        package, its version, your operating system, and your operating
        system's version in this prompt. Just blindly follow the instructions
        it provides. This is always fairly accurate, on account of this being
        a <emphasis>very</emphasis> common question with very straightforward
        steps which have been invariant for the better part of two
        decades.</para>

        <tip>
          <para>If you are using macOS you will most likely have to also
          install <link xlink:href="https://brew.sh/"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">HomeBrew</link>. This is
          a safe piece of software we use ourselves, too.</para>
        </tip>

        <para><bridgehead>Self-hosting (Linux, *BSD)</bridgehead></para>

        <para>Many people choose to run their own Linux or *BSD server or
        desktop, for development and / or production. We do too! Several, in
        fact.</para>

        <para>Before you begin, you will need to install the
        <code>imagick</code> extension package on your system. Assuming you're
        using the default PHP version that comes with your distribution, this
        is usually as follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Debian, Ubuntu and their derivatives: <command>sudo
            apt-install -y php-imagick</command></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Arch Linux and its derivatives: <command>sudo pacman -Syu
            php-imagick</command></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>RedHat, CentOS, Alma Linux, and their derivatives:
            <command>sudo dnf install -y php-pecl-imagick</command></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>FreeBSD and its derivatives (replace
            <replaceable>php82</replaceable> with your PHP version):
            <command>sudo pkg install -y imagemagick &amp;&amp; sudo pkg
            install -y php82-pecl-imagick</command></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>NetBSD, OpenBSD, and their derivatives: you need to compile
            the extension yourself.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>After installing the extension, make sure it's enabled by
        running <command>php -m | grep imagick</command>. If
        <code>imagick</code> is enabled, you will see the result
        <code>imagick</code> coming back.</para>

        <screen>$ php -m | grep imagick
imagick</screen>

        <para>If this is not the case, you probably have to edit your
        <filename>php.ini</filename> file. First, find out where it lives with
        <command>php --ini</command>.</para>

        <screen>$ php --ini
Configuration File (php.ini) Path: /etc/php
Loaded Configuration File:         <emphasis role="bold">/etc/php/php.ini</emphasis>
Scan for additional .ini files in: /etc/php/conf.d
Additional .ini files parsed:      /etc/php/conf.d/99-nicholas.ini,
/etc/php/conf.d/igbinary.ini,
/etc/php/conf.d/imagick.ini,
/etc/php/conf.d/memcached.ini,
/etc/php/conf.d/redis.ini,
/etc/php/conf.d/xdebug.ini</screen>

        <para>The "Loaded Configuration File" is your main
        <filename>php.ini</filename> file. You can try to edit it with
        <command>sudo sed -i '/;extension=imagick.so/s/^;//'
        /etc/php/php.ini</command> This command uncomments the line which
        loads the <code>imagick</code> extension, assuming it was present in
        your <filename>php.ini</filename>file (that's the default).</para>

        <para>Alternatively, you can create a new INI file in the "Scan for
        additional .ini files in" directory. In our example above you can see
        that this is what we have done; we created the file
        <filename>/etc/php/conf.d/imagick.ini</filename> with these
        contents:</para>

        <programlisting>extension = imagick</programlisting>

        <para>Sometimes, your distribution's package manager
        <emphasis>may</emphasis> create such an additional INI file, but have
        the <code>extension</code> line commented out. For example, this is
        the default behaviour in Arch Linux. Edit the file, and remove the
        comment marker (<code>;</code>) from the start of the line.</para>

        <note>
          <para>You may have noticed that in one instance we have
          <code>extension=imagick.so</code> and in the other we have
          <code>extension=imagick</code>. They are equivalent and work the
          same on Linux and *BSD. You can use either; it's a matter of
          preference. The latter form is easier to read, which is why some
          distributions –like Arch Linux– default to it.</para>
        </note>

        <para>After you are done editing your <filename>php.ini</filename>
        file, please remember to restart your web server AND PHP-FPM (if you
        are using PHP-FPM). How to do that depends on your distribution and
        installed PHP version. For example, on Debian and Ubuntu you need to
        do <command>systemctl restart php8.2-fpm &amp;&amp; systemctl restart
        apache2</command> whereas on Arch Linux you need to do
        <command>systemctl restart php83-fpm &amp;&amp; systemctl restart
        httpd</command>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="clean-up-old-images">
      <title>Cleaning up old images</title>

      <para>SocialMagick creates OpenGraph images. The generated image files
      are stored on your site, by default under
      <filename>media/com_socialmagick/generated</filename>. This happens for
      two reasons. First of all, generating images is time consuming. Having
      the generated images cached means that this time will only be spent
      once, speeding up your site. Second, when you are sharing a link to a
      site or application it will retrieve the URL of the OpenGraph image, not
      necessarily its contents right away. The image must remain available on
      your site for link previews to work. This behaviour depends on the third
      party site / application. For this reason, SocialMagick will by default
      never clean up old images.</para>

      <para>The image filename is constructed as a hash of the page of your
      site you are displaying, the template ID and summary of its options, as
      well as the Text and the location of the Extra Image used to generate
      the image. When any of these factors change, so does the image filename.
      When you are actively working on your site, tuning the SocialMagick
      templates, changing the menu item OpenGraph options etc a lot of images
      will be generated.</para>

      <para>Moreover, as we said, old images are never removed, even if the
      page has not been viewed for a very long time. This leaves behind the
      OpenGraph image.</para>

      <para>Depending on the image format you use, these images can get quite
      big. PNG format images are the biggest, usually around 1-2 MiB each,
      whereas WebP images are the smallest, usually in the 100-200 KiB
      range.</para>

      <para>If you are short on space you may want to remove old OpenGraph
      images. There are two ways to do that.</para>

      <para>First, when you visit the SocialMagick Templates page in the
      backend you can see how much space your OpenGraph images take and delete
      all of them. They will be regenerated on demand.</para>

      <para>Second, as long as you publish the <guilabel>Task -
      SocialMagick</guilabel> plugin you can use Joomla's Scheduled Tasks
      feature to create a scheduled task of the <guilabel>SocialMagick -
      Delete Obsolete Images</guilabel> type to automatically delete images
      older than a specific amount of time, from 1 minute to 1 year.</para>

      <para>That said, we recommend AGAINST deleting old OpenGraph images on a
      production site. A production site will be indexed by search engine
      crawlers which access all of your site's pages sequentially. If these
      pages are set to generate OpenGraph images and these images are missing
      from your site, they will have to be generated. This takes up a lot of
      server resources. Therefore, crawling your site could have a <emphasis
      role="bold">MASSIVE</emphasis> impact in its performance if the
      OpenGraph images of old pages nobody but the crawler ever
      accesses!</para>

      <para>If you are concerned about disk space and site performance, we
      recommend having OpenGraph image generation turned off by default, and
      only enable it for specific pages which you reasonably expect to be
      shared and would like to have custom OpenGraph images. For instance, a
      device manufacturer's site would likely want to enable OpenGraph images
      for the site's products and news sections, but not its community forum,
      and downloads / resources sections.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <appendix xml:id="gpl">
    <title><acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License version 3</title>

    <para>Version 3, 29 June 2007</para>

    <para>Copyright © 2007 Free Software Foundation, Inc. <link
    xlink:href="http://fsf.org/"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://fsf.org/</link></para>

    <para>Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of this
    license document, but changing it is not allowed.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="Preamble">Preamble</bridgehead>

    <para>The <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License is a free,
    copyleft license for software and other kinds of works.</para>

    <para>The licenses for most software and other practical works are
    designed to take away your freedom to share and change the works. By
    contrast, the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License is intended to
    guarantee your freedom to share and change all versions of a program—to
    make sure it remains free software for all its users. We, the Free
    Software Foundation, use the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License
    for most of our software; it applies also to any other work released this
    way by its authors. You can apply it to your programs, too.</para>

    <para>When we speak of free software, we are referring to freedom, not
    price. Our General Public Licenses are designed to make sure that you have
    the freedom to distribute copies of free software (and charge for them if
    you wish), that you receive source code or can get it if you want it, that
    you can change the software or use pieces of it in new free programs, and
    that you know you can do these things.</para>

    <para>To protect your rights, we need to prevent others from denying you
    these rights or asking you to surrender the rights. Therefore, you have
    certain responsibilities if you distribute copies of the software, or if
    you modify it: responsibilities to respect the freedom of others.</para>

    <para>For example, if you distribute copies of such a program, whether
    gratis or for a fee, you must pass on to the recipients the same freedoms
    that you received. You must make sure that they, too, receive or can get
    the source code. And you must show them these terms so they know their
    rights.</para>

    <para>Developers that use the <acronym>GNU</acronym>
    <acronym>GPL</acronym> protect your rights with two steps: (1) assert
    copyright on the software, and (2) offer you this License giving you legal
    permission to copy, distribute and/or modify it.</para>

    <para>For the developers' and authors' protection, the
    <acronym>GPL</acronym> clearly explains that there is no warranty for this
    free software. For both users' and authors' sake, the
    <acronym>GPL</acronym> requires that modified versions be marked as
    changed, so that their problems will not be attributed erroneously to
    authors of previous versions.</para>

    <para>Some devices are designed to deny users access to install or run
    modified versions of the software inside them, although the manufacturer
    can do so. This is fundamentally incompatible with the aim of protecting
    users' freedom to change the software. The systematic pattern of such
    abuse occurs in the area of products for individuals to use, which is
    precisely where it is most unacceptable. Therefore, we have designed this
    version of the <acronym>GPL</acronym> to prohibit the practice for those
    products. If such problems arise substantially in other domains, we stand
    ready to extend this provision to those domains in future versions of the
    <acronym>GPL</acronym>, as needed to protect the freedom of users.</para>

    <para>Finally, every program is threatened constantly by software patents.
    States should not allow patents to restrict development and use of
    software on general-purpose computers, but in those that do, we wish to
    avoid the special danger that patents applied to a free program could make
    it effectively proprietary. To prevent this, the <acronym>GPL</acronym>
    assures that patents cannot be used to render the program non-free.</para>

    <para>The precise terms and conditions for copying, distribution and
    modification follow.</para>

    <bridgehead>TERMS AND CONDITIONS</bridgehead>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="Definitions">0.
    Definitions.</bridgehead>

    <para>“This License” refers to version 3 of the <acronym>GNU</acronym>
    General Public License.</para>

    <para>“Copyright” also means copyright-like laws that apply to other kinds
    of works, such as semiconductor masks.</para>

    <para>“The Program” refers to any copyrightable work licensed under this
    License. Each licensee is addressed as “you”. “Licensees” and “recipients”
    may be individuals or organizations.</para>

    <para>To “modify” a work means to copy from or adapt all or part of the
    work in a fashion requiring copyright permission, other than the making of
    an exact copy. The resulting work is called a “modified version” of the
    earlier work or a work “based on” the earlier work.</para>

    <para>A “covered work” means either the unmodified Program or a work based
    on the Program.</para>

    <para>To “propagate” a work means to do anything with it that, without
    permission, would make you directly or secondarily liable for infringement
    under applicable copyright law, except executing it on a computer or
    modifying a private copy. Propagation includes copying, distribution (with
    or without modification), making available to the public, and in some
    countries other activities as well.</para>

    <para>To “convey” a work means any kind of propagation that enables other
    parties to make or receive copies. Mere interaction with a user through a
    computer network, with no transfer of a copy, is not conveying.</para>

    <para>An interactive user interface displays “Appropriate Legal Notices”
    to the extent that it includes a convenient and prominently visible
    feature that (1) displays an appropriate copyright notice, and (2) tells
    the user that there is no warranty for the work (except to the extent that
    warranties are provided), that licensees may convey the work under this
    License, and how to view a copy of this License. If the interface presents
    a list of user commands or options, such as a menu, a prominent item in
    the list meets this criterion.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="SourceCode">1. Source
    Code.</bridgehead>

    <para>The “source code” for a work means the preferred form of the work
    for making modifications to it. “Object code” means any non-source form of
    a work.</para>

    <para>A “Standard Interface” means an interface that either is an official
    standard defined by a recognized standards body, or, in the case of
    interfaces specified for a particular programming language, one that is
    widely used among developers working in that language.</para>

    <para>The “System Libraries” of an executable work include anything, other
    than the work as a whole, that (a) is included in the normal form of
    packaging a Major Component, but which is not part of that Major
    Component, and (b) serves only to enable use of the work with that Major
    Component, or to implement a Standard Interface for which an
    implementation is available to the public in source code form. A “Major
    Component”, in this context, means a major essential component (kernel,
    window system, and so on) of the specific operating system (if any) on
    which the executable work runs, or a compiler used to produce the work, or
    an object code interpreter used to run it.</para>

    <para>The “Corresponding Source” for a work in object code form means all
    the source code needed to generate, install, and (for an executable work)
    run the object code and to modify the work, including scripts to control
    those activities. However, it does not include the work's System
    Libraries, or general-purpose tools or generally available free programs
    which are used unmodified in performing those activities but which are not
    part of the work. For example, Corresponding Source includes interface
    definition files associated with source files for the work, and the source
    code for shared libraries and dynamically linked subprograms that the work
    is specifically designed to require, such as by intimate data
    communication or control flow between those subprograms and other parts of
    the work.</para>

    <para>The Corresponding Source need not include anything that users can
    regenerate automatically from other parts of the Corresponding
    Source.</para>

    <para>The Corresponding Source for a work in source code form is that same
    work.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="BasicPermissions">2. Basic
    Permissions.</bridgehead>

    <para>All rights granted under this License are granted for the term of
    copyright on the Program, and are irrevocable provided the stated
    conditions are met. This License explicitly affirms your unlimited
    permission to run the unmodified Program. The output from running a
    covered work is covered by this License only if the output, given its
    content, constitutes a covered work. This License acknowledges your rights
    of fair use or other equivalent, as provided by copyright law.</para>

    <para>You may make, run and propagate covered works that you do not
    convey, without conditions so long as your license otherwise remains in
    force. You may convey covered works to others for the sole purpose of
    having them make modifications exclusively for you, or provide you with
    facilities for running those works, provided that you comply with the
    terms of this License in conveying all material for which you do not
    control copyright. Those thus making or running the covered works for you
    must do so exclusively on your behalf, under your direction and control,
    on terms that prohibit them from making any copies of your copyrighted
    material outside their relationship with you.</para>

    <para>Conveying under any other circumstances is permitted solely under
    the conditions stated below. Sublicensing is not allowed; section 10 makes
    it unnecessary.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="Protecting">3. Protecting Users'
    Legal Rights From Anti-Circumvention Law.</bridgehead>

    <para>No covered work shall be deemed part of an effective technological
    measure under any applicable law fulfilling obligations under article 11
    of the WIPO copyright treaty adopted on 20 December 1996, or similar laws
    prohibiting or restricting circumvention of such measures.</para>

    <para>When you convey a covered work, you waive any legal power to forbid
    circumvention of technological measures to the extent such circumvention
    is effected by exercising rights under this License with respect to the
    covered work, and you disclaim any intention to limit operation or
    modification of the work as a means of enforcing, against the work's
    users, your or third parties' legal rights to forbid circumvention of
    technological measures.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="ConveyingVerbatim">4. Conveying
    Verbatim Copies.</bridgehead>

    <para>You may convey verbatim copies of the Program's source code as you
    receive it, in any medium, provided that you conspicuously and
    appropriately publish on each copy an appropriate copyright notice; keep
    intact all notices stating that this License and any non-permissive terms
    added in accord with section 7 apply to the code; keep intact all notices
    of the absence of any warranty; and give all recipients a copy of this
    License along with the Program.</para>

    <para>You may charge any price or no price for each copy that you convey,
    and you may offer support or warranty protection for a fee.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="ConveyingModified">5. Conveying
    Modified Source Versions.</bridgehead>

    <para>You may convey a work based on the Program, or the modifications to
    produce it from the Program, in the form of source code under the terms of
    section 4, provided that you also meet all of these conditions:</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
      <listitem>
        <para>The work must carry prominent notices stating that you modified
        it, and giving a relevant date.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The work must carry prominent notices stating that it is
        released under this License and any conditions added under section 7.
        This requirement modifies the requirement in section 4 to “keep intact
        all notices”.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You must license the entire work, as a whole, under this License
        to anyone who comes into possession of a copy. This License will
        therefore apply, along with any applicable section 7 additional terms,
        to the whole of the work, and all its parts, regardless of how they
        are packaged. This License gives no permission to license the work in
        any other way, but it does not invalidate such permission if you have
        separately received it.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If the work has interactive user interfaces, each must display
        Appropriate Legal Notices; however, if the Program has interactive
        interfaces that do not display Appropriate Legal Notices, your work
        need not make them do so.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>A compilation of a covered work with other separate and independent
    works, which are not by their nature extensions of the covered work, and
    which are not combined with it such as to form a larger program, in or on
    a volume of a storage or distribution medium, is called an “aggregate” if
    the compilation and its resulting copyright are not used to limit the
    access or legal rights of the compilation's users beyond what the
    individual works permit. Inclusion of a covered work in an aggregate does
    not cause this License to apply to the other parts of the
    aggregate.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="ConveyingNonSource">6. Conveying
    Non-Source Forms.</bridgehead>

    <para>You may convey a covered work in object code form under the terms of
    sections 4 and 5, provided that you also convey the machine-readable
    Corresponding Source under the terms of this License, in one of these
    ways:</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
      <listitem>
        <para>Convey the object code in, or embodied in, a physical product
        (including a physical distribution medium), accompanied by the
        Corresponding Source fixed on a durable physical medium customarily
        used for software interchange.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Convey the object code in, or embodied in, a physical product
        (including a physical distribution medium), accompanied by a written
        offer, valid for at least three years and valid for as long as you
        offer spare parts or customer support for that product model, to give
        anyone who possesses the object code either (1) a copy of the
        Corresponding Source for all the software in the product that is
        covered by this License, on a durable physical medium customarily used
        for software interchange, for a price no more than your reasonable
        cost of physically performing this conveying of source, or (2) access
        to copy the Corresponding Source from a network server at no
        charge.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Convey individual copies of the object code with a copy of the
        written offer to provide the Corresponding Source. This alternative is
        allowed only occasionally and noncommercially, and only if you
        received the object code with such an offer, in accord with subsection
        6b.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Convey the object code by offering access from a designated
        place (gratis or for a charge), and offer equivalent access to the
        Corresponding Source in the same way through the same place at no
        further charge. You need not require recipients to copy the
        Corresponding Source along with the object code. If the place to copy
        the object code is a network server, the Corresponding Source may be
        on a different server (operated by you or a third party) that supports
        equivalent copying facilities, provided you maintain clear directions
        next to the object code saying where to find the Corresponding Source.
        Regardless of what server hosts the Corresponding Source, you remain
        obligated to ensure that it is available for as long as needed to
        satisfy these requirements.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Convey the object code using peer-to-peer transmission, provided
        you inform other peers where the object code and Corresponding Source
        of the work are being offered to the general public at no charge under
        subsection 6d.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>A separable portion of the object code, whose source code is
    excluded from the Corresponding Source as a System Library, need not be
    included in conveying the object code work.</para>

    <para>A “User Product” is either (1) a “consumer product”, which means any
    tangible personal property which is normally used for personal, family, or
    household purposes, or (2) anything designed or sold for incorporation
    into a dwelling. In determining whether a product is a consumer product,
    doubtful cases shall be resolved in favor of coverage. For a particular
    product received by a particular user, “normally used” refers to a typical
    or common use of that class of product, regardless of the status of the
    particular user or of the way in which the particular user actually uses,
    or expects or is expected to use, the product. A product is a consumer
    product regardless of whether the product has substantial commercial,
    industrial or non-consumer uses, unless such uses represent the only
    significant mode of use of the product.</para>

    <para>“Installation Information” for a User Product means any methods,
    procedures, authorization keys, or other information required to install
    and execute modified versions of a covered work in that User Product from
    a modified version of its Corresponding Source. The information must
    suffice to ensure that the continued functioning of the modified object
    code is in no case prevented or interfered with solely because
    modification has been made.</para>

    <para>If you convey an object code work under this section in, or with, or
    specifically for use in, a User Product, and the conveying occurs as part
    of a transaction in which the right of possession and use of the User
    Product is transferred to the recipient in perpetuity or for a fixed term
    (regardless of how the transaction is characterized), the Corresponding
    Source conveyed under this section must be accompanied by the Installation
    Information. But this requirement does not apply if neither you nor any
    third party retains the ability to install modified object code on the
    User Product (for example, the work has been installed in
    <acronym>ROM</acronym>).</para>

    <para>The requirement to provide Installation Information does not include
    a requirement to continue to provide support service, warranty, or updates
    for a work that has been modified or installed by the recipient, or for
    the User Product in which it has been modified or installed. Access to a
    network may be denied when the modification itself materially and
    adversely affects the operation of the network or violates the rules and
    protocols for communication across the network.</para>

    <para>Corresponding Source conveyed, and Installation Information
    provided, in accord with this section must be in a format that is publicly
    documented (and with an implementation available to the public in source
    code form), and must require no special password or key for unpacking,
    reading or copying.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="AdditionalTerms">7. Additional
    Terms.</bridgehead>

    <para>“Additional permissions” are terms that supplement the terms of this
    License by making exceptions from one or more of its conditions.
    Additional permissions that are applicable to the entire Program shall be
    treated as though they were included in this License, to the extent that
    they are valid under applicable law. If additional permissions apply only
    to part of the Program, that part may be used separately under those
    permissions, but the entire Program remains governed by this License
    without regard to the additional permissions.</para>

    <para>When you convey a copy of a covered work, you may at your option
    remove any additional permissions from that copy, or from any part of it.
    (Additional permissions may be written to require their own removal in
    certain cases when you modify the work.) You may place additional
    permissions on material, added by you to a covered work, for which you
    have or can give appropriate copyright permission.</para>

    <para>Notwithstanding any other provision of this License, for material
    you add to a covered work, you may (if authorized by the copyright holders
    of that material) supplement the terms of this License with terms:</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
      <listitem>
        <para>Disclaiming warranty or limiting liability differently from the
        terms of sections 15 and 16 of this License; or</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Requiring preservation of specified reasonable legal notices or
        author attributions in that material or in the Appropriate Legal
        Notices displayed by works containing it; or</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Prohibiting misrepresentation of the origin of that material, or
        requiring that modified versions of such material be marked in
        reasonable ways as different from the original version; or</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Limiting the use for publicity purposes of names of licensors or
        authors of the material; or</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Declining to grant rights under trademark law for use of some
        trade names, trademarks, or service marks; or</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Requiring indemnification of licensors and authors of that
        material by anyone who conveys the material (or modified versions of
        it) with contractual assumptions of liability to the recipient, for
        any liability that these contractual assumptions directly impose on
        those licensors and authors.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>All other non-permissive additional terms are considered “further
    restrictions” within the meaning of section 10. If the Program as you
    received it, or any part of it, contains a notice stating that it is
    governed by this License along with a term that is a further restriction,
    you may remove that term. If a license document contains a further
    restriction but permits relicensing or conveying under this License, you
    may add to a covered work material governed by the terms of that license
    document, provided that the further restriction does not survive such
    relicensing or conveying.</para>

    <para>If you add terms to a covered work in accord with this section, you
    must place, in the relevant source files, a statement of the additional
    terms that apply to those files, or a notice indicating where to find the
    applicable terms.</para>

    <para>Additional terms, permissive or non-permissive, may be stated in the
    form of a separately written license, or stated as exceptions; the above
    requirements apply either way.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="Termination">8.
    Termination.</bridgehead>

    <para>You may not propagate or modify a covered work except as expressly
    provided under this License. Any attempt otherwise to propagate or modify
    it is void, and will automatically terminate your rights under this
    License (including any patent licenses granted under the third paragraph
    of section 11).</para>

    <para>However, if you cease all violation of this License, then your
    license from a particular copyright holder is reinstated (a)
    provisionally, unless and until the copyright holder explicitly and
    finally terminates your license, and (b) permanently, if the copyright
    holder fails to notify you of the violation by some reasonable means prior
    to 60 days after the cessation.</para>

    <para>Moreover, your license from a particular copyright holder is
    reinstated permanently if the copyright holder notifies you of the
    violation by some reasonable means, this is the first time you have
    received notice of violation of this License (for any work) from that
    copyright holder, and you cure the violation prior to 30 days after your
    receipt of the notice.</para>

    <para>Termination of your rights under this section does not terminate the
    licenses of parties who have received copies or rights from you under this
    License. If your rights have been terminated and not permanently
    reinstated, you do not qualify to receive new licenses for the same
    material under section 10.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="AcceptanceNotRequired">9. Acceptance
    Not Required for Having Copies.</bridgehead>

    <para>You are not required to accept this License in order to receive or
    run a copy of the Program. Ancillary propagation of a covered work
    occurring solely as a consequence of using peer-to-peer transmission to
    receive a copy likewise does not require acceptance. However, nothing
    other than this License grants you permission to propagate or modify any
    covered work. These actions infringe copyright if you do not accept this
    License. Therefore, by modifying or propagating a covered work, you
    indicate your acceptance of this License to do so.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="AutomaticDownstream">10. Automatic
    Licensing of Downstream Recipients.</bridgehead>

    <para>Each time you convey a covered work, the recipient automatically
    receives a license from the original licensors, to run, modify and
    propagate that work, subject to this License. You are not responsible for
    enforcing compliance by third parties with this License.</para>

    <para>An “entity transaction” is a transaction transferring control of an
    organization, or substantially all assets of one, or subdividing an
    organization, or merging organizations. If propagation of a covered work
    results from an entity transaction, each party to that transaction who
    receives a copy of the work also receives whatever licenses to the work
    the party's predecessor in interest had or could give under the previous
    paragraph, plus a right to possession of the Corresponding Source of the
    work from the predecessor in interest, if the predecessor has it or can
    get it with reasonable efforts.</para>

    <para>You may not impose any further restrictions on the exercise of the
    rights granted or affirmed under this License. For example, you may not
    impose a license fee, royalty, or other charge for exercise of rights
    granted under this License, and you may not initiate litigation (including
    a cross-claim or counterclaim in a lawsuit) alleging that any patent claim
    is infringed by making, using, selling, offering for sale, or importing
    the Program or any portion of it.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="Patents">11. Patents.</bridgehead>

    <para>A “contributor” is a copyright holder who authorizes use under this
    License of the Program or a work on which the Program is based. The work
    thus licensed is called the contributor's “contributor version”.</para>

    <para>A contributor's “essential patent claims” are all patent claims
    owned or controlled by the contributor, whether already acquired or
    hereafter acquired, that would be infringed by some manner, permitted by
    this License, of making, using, or selling its contributor version, but do
    not include claims that would be infringed only as a consequence of
    further modification of the contributor version. For purposes of this
    definition, “control” includes the right to grant patent sublicenses in a
    manner consistent with the requirements of this License.</para>

    <para>Each contributor grants you a non-exclusive, worldwide, royalty-free
    patent license under the contributor's essential patent claims, to make,
    use, sell, offer for sale, import and otherwise run, modify and propagate
    the contents of its contributor version.</para>

    <para>In the following three paragraphs, a “patent license” is any express
    agreement or commitment, however denominated, not to enforce a patent
    (such as an express permission to practice a patent or covenant not to sue
    for patent infringement). To “grant” such a patent license to a party
    means to make such an agreement or commitment not to enforce a patent
    against the party.</para>

    <para>If you convey a covered work, knowingly relying on a patent license,
    and the Corresponding Source of the work is not available for anyone to
    copy, free of charge and under the terms of this License, through a
    publicly available network server or other readily accessible means, then
    you must either (1) cause the Corresponding Source to be so available, or
    (2) arrange to deprive yourself of the benefit of the patent license for
    this particular work, or (3) arrange, in a manner consistent with the
    requirements of this License, to extend the patent license to downstream
    recipients. “Knowingly relying” means you have actual knowledge that, but
    for the patent license, your conveying the covered work in a country, or
    your recipient's use of the covered work in a country, would infringe one
    or more identifiable patents in that country that you have reason to
    believe are valid.</para>

    <para>If, pursuant to or in connection with a single transaction or
    arrangement, you convey, or propagate by procuring conveyance of, a
    covered work, and grant a patent license to some of the parties receiving
    the covered work authorizing them to use, propagate, modify or convey a
    specific copy of the covered work, then the patent license you grant is
    automatically extended to all recipients of the covered work and works
    based on it.</para>

    <para>A patent license is “discriminatory” if it does not include within
    the scope of its coverage, prohibits the exercise of, or is conditioned on
    the non-exercise of one or more of the rights that are specifically
    granted under this License. You may not convey a covered work if you are a
    party to an arrangement with a third party that is in the business of
    distributing software, under which you make payment to the third party
    based on the extent of your activity of conveying the work, and under
    which the third party grants, to any of the parties who would receive the
    covered work from you, a discriminatory patent license (a) in connection
    with copies of the covered work conveyed by you (or copies made from those
    copies), or (b) primarily for and in connection with specific products or
    compilations that contain the covered work, unless you entered into that
    arrangement, or that patent license was granted, prior to 28 March
    2007.</para>

    <para>Nothing in this License shall be construed as excluding or limiting
    any implied license or other defenses to infringement that may otherwise
    be available to you under applicable patent law.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="NoSurrender">12. No Surrender of
    Others' Freedom.</bridgehead>

    <para>If conditions are imposed on you (whether by court order, agreement
    or otherwise) that contradict the conditions of this License, they do not
    excuse you from the conditions of this License. If you cannot convey a
    covered work so as to satisfy simultaneously your obligations under this
    License and any other pertinent obligations, then as a consequence you may
    not convey it at all. For example, if you agree to terms that obligate you
    to collect a royalty for further conveying from those to whom you convey
    the Program, the only way you could satisfy both those terms and this
    License would be to refrain entirely from conveying the Program.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="UsedWithAGPL">13. Use with the
    <acronym>GNU</acronym> Affero General Public License.</bridgehead>

    <para>Notwithstanding any other provision of this License, you have
    permission to link or combine any covered work with a work licensed under
    version 3 of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> Affero General Public License into
    a single combined work, and to convey the resulting work. The terms of
    this License will continue to apply to the part which is the covered work,
    but the special requirements of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> Affero General
    Public License, section 13, concerning interaction through a network will
    apply to the combination as such.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="RevisedVersions">14. Revised Versions
    of this License.</bridgehead>

    <para>The Free Software Foundation may publish revised and/or new versions
    of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License from time to time.
    Such new versions will be similar in spirit to the present version, but
    may differ in detail to address new problems or concerns.</para>

    <para>Each version is given a distinguishing version number. If the
    Program specifies that a certain numbered version of the
    <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License “or any later version”
    applies to it, you have the option of following the terms and conditions
    either of that numbered version or of any later version published by the
    Free Software Foundation. If the Program does not specify a version number
    of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License, you may choose any
    version ever published by the Free Software Foundation.</para>

    <para>If the Program specifies that a proxy can decide which future
    versions of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License can be used,
    that proxy's public statement of acceptance of a version permanently
    authorizes you to choose that version for the Program.</para>

    <para>Later license versions may give you additional or different
    permissions. However, no additional obligations are imposed on any author
    or copyright holder as a result of your choosing to follow a later
    version.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="WarrantyDisclaimer">15. Disclaimer of
    Warranty.</bridgehead>

    <para>THERE IS NO WARRANTY FOR THE PROGRAM, TO THE EXTENT PERMITTED BY
    APPLICABLE LAW. EXCEPT WHEN OTHERWISE STATED IN WRITING THE COPYRIGHT
    HOLDERS AND/OR OTHER PARTIES PROVIDE THE PROGRAM “AS IS” WITHOUT WARRANTY
    OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO,
    THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
    PURPOSE. THE ENTIRE RISK AS TO THE QUALITY AND PERFORMANCE OF THE PROGRAM
    IS WITH YOU. SHOULD THE PROGRAM PROVE DEFECTIVE, YOU ASSUME THE COST OF
    ALL NECESSARY SERVICING, REPAIR OR CORRECTION.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="LiabilityLimitation">16. Limitation
    of Liability.</bridgehead>

    <para>IN NO EVENT UNLESS REQUIRED BY APPLICABLE LAW OR AGREED TO IN
    WRITING WILL ANY COPYRIGHT HOLDER, OR ANY OTHER PARTY WHO MODIFIES AND/OR
    CONVEYS THE PROGRAM AS PERMITTED ABOVE, BE LIABLE TO YOU FOR DAMAGES,
    INCLUDING ANY GENERAL, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
    ARISING OUT OF THE USE OR INABILITY TO USE THE PROGRAM (INCLUDING BUT NOT
    LIMITED TO LOSS OF DATA OR DATA BEING RENDERED INACCURATE OR LOSSES
    SUSTAINED BY YOU OR THIRD PARTIES OR A FAILURE OF THE PROGRAM TO OPERATE
    WITH ANY OTHER PROGRAMS), EVEN IF SUCH HOLDER OR OTHER PARTY HAS BEEN
    ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="InterpretationSecs1516">17.
    Interpretation of Sections 15 and 16.</bridgehead>

    <para>If the disclaimer of warranty and limitation of liability provided
    above cannot be given local legal effect according to their terms,
    reviewing courts shall apply local law that most closely approximates an
    absolute waiver of all civil liability in connection with the Program,
    unless a warranty or assumption of liability accompanies a copy of the
    Program in return for a fee.</para>

    <bridgehead>END OF TERMS AND CONDITIONS</bridgehead>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="HowToApply">How to Apply These Terms
    to Your New Programs</bridgehead>

    <para>If you develop a new program, and you want it to be of the greatest
    possible use to the public, the best way to achieve this is to make it
    free software which everyone can redistribute and change under these
    terms.</para>

    <para>To do so, attach the following notices to the program. It is safest
    to attach them to the start of each source file to most effectively state
    the exclusion of warranty; and each file should have at least the
    “copyright” line and a pointer to where the full notice is found.</para>

    <screen>
            <replaceable>one line to give the program's name and a brief idea of what it does.</replaceable>
            Copyright (C) <replaceable>year</replaceable> <replaceable>name of author</replaceable>

            This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
            it under the terms of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License as published by
            the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or
            (at your option) any later version.

            This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
            but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
            MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
            <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License for more details.

            You should have received a copy of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License
            along with this program.  If not, see <link
        xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/</link>.
        </screen>

    <para>Also add information on how to contact you by electronic and paper
    mail.</para>

    <para>If the program does terminal interaction, make it output a short
    notice like this when it starts in an interactive mode:</para>

    <screen>
            <replaceable>program</replaceable> Copyright (C) <replaceable>year</replaceable> <replaceable>name of author</replaceable>
            This program comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY; for details type '<literal>show w</literal>'.
            This is free software, and you are welcome to redistribute it
            under certain conditions; type '<literal>show c</literal>' for details.
        </screen>

    <para>The hypothetical commands '<literal>show w</literal>' and
    '<literal>show c</literal>' should show the appropriate parts of the
    General Public License. Of course, your program's commands might be
    different; for a GUI interface, you would use an “about box”.</para>

    <para>You should also get your employer (if you work as a programmer) or
    school, if any, to sign a “copyright disclaimer” for the program, if
    necessary. For more information on this, and how to apply and follow the
    <acronym>GNU</acronym> <acronym>GPL</acronym>, see <link
    xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/</link>.</para>

    <para>The <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License does not permit
    incorporating your program into proprietary programs. If your program is a
    subroutine library, you may consider it more useful to permit linking
    proprietary applications with the library. If this is what you want to do,
    use the <acronym>GNU</acronym> Lesser General Public License instead of
    this License. But first, please read <link
    xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/why-not-lgpl.html"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/why-not-lgpl.html</link>.</para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix xml:id="fdl">
    <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>

    <simpara>Version 1.3, 3 November 2008</simpara>

    <simpara>Copyright © 2000, 2001, 2002, 2007, 2008 <link
    xlink:href="http://www.fsf.org/"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Free Software Foundation,
    Inc.</link></simpara>

    <simpara>Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of
    this license document, but changing it is not allowed.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section0">0. PREAMBLE</bridgehead>

    <simpara>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or
    other functional and useful document “free” in the sense of freedom: to
    assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with or
    without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially. Secondarily,
    this License preserves for the author and publisher a way to get credit
    for their work, while not being considered responsible for modifications
    made by others.</simpara>

    <simpara>This License is a kind of “copyleft”, which means that derivative
    works of the document must themselves be free in the same sense. It
    complements the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license
    designed for free software.</simpara>

    <simpara>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for
    free software, because free software needs free documentation: a free
    program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the
    software does. But this License is not limited to software manuals; it can
    be used for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or whether it
    is published as a printed book. We recommend this License principally for
    works whose purpose is instruction or reference.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section1">1. APPLICABILITY AND
    DEFINITIONS</bridgehead>

    <simpara>This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium,
    that contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
    distributed under the terms of this License. Such a notice grants a
    world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that work
    under the conditions stated herein. The “Document”, below, refers to any
    such manual or work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and is
    addressed as “you”. You accept the license if you copy, modify or
    distribute the work in a way requiring permission under copyright
    law.</simpara>

    <simpara>A “Modified Version” of the Document means any work containing
    the Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with
    modifications and/or translated into another language.</simpara>

    <simpara>A “Secondary Section” is a named appendix or a front-matter
    section of the Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of
    the publishers or authors of the Document to the Document’s overall
    subject (or to related matters) and contains nothing that could fall
    directly within that overall subject. (Thus, if the Document is in part a
    textbook of mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any
    mathematics.) The relationship could be a matter of historical connection
    with the subject or with related matters, or of legal, commercial,
    philosophical, ethical or political position regarding them.</simpara>

    <simpara>The “Invariant Sections” are certain Secondary Sections whose
    titles are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the notice
    that says that the Document is released under this License. If a section
    does not fit the above definition of Secondary then it is not allowed to
    be designated as Invariant. The Document may contain zero Invariant
    Sections. If the Document does not identify any Invariant Sections then
    there are none.</simpara>

    <simpara>The “Cover Texts” are certain short passages of text that are
    listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says
    that the Document is released under this License. A Front-Cover Text may
    be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25
    words.</simpara>

    <simpara>A “Transparent” copy of the Document means a machine-readable
    copy, represented in a format whose specification is available to the
    general public, that is suitable for revising the document
    straightforwardly with generic text editors or (for images composed of
    pixels) generic paint programs or (for drawings) some widely available
    drawing editor, and that is suitable for input to text formatters or for
    automatic translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text
    formatters. A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format whose
    markup, or absence of markup, has been arranged to thwart or discourage
    subsequent modification by readers is not Transparent. An image format is
    not Transparent if used for any substantial amount of text. A copy that is
    not “Transparent” is called “Opaque”.</simpara>

    <simpara>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain
    ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or
    XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML,
    PostScript or PDF designed for human modification. Examples of transparent
    image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG. Opaque formats include proprietary
    formats that can be read and edited only by proprietary word processors,
    SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally
    available, and the machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by
    some word processors for output purposes only.</simpara>

    <simpara>The “Title Page” means, for a printed book, the title page
    itself, plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the
    material this License requires to appear in the title page. For works in
    formats which do not have any title page as such, “Title Page” means the
    text near the most prominent appearance of the work’s title, preceding the
    beginning of the body of the text.</simpara>

    <simpara>The “publisher” means any person or entity that distributes
    copies of the Document to the public.</simpara>

    <simpara>A section “Entitled XYZ” means a named subunit of the Document
    whose title either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses
    following text that translates XYZ in another language. (Here XYZ stands
    for a specific section name mentioned below, such as “Acknowledgements”,
    “Dedications”, “Endorsements”, or “History”.) To “Preserve the Title” of
    such a section when you modify the Document means that it remains a
    section “Entitled XYZ” according to this definition.</simpara>

    <simpara>The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice
    which states that this License applies to the Document. These Warranty
    Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this License,
    but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other implication that
    these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has no effect on the
    meaning of this License.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section2">2. VERBATIM
    COPYING</bridgehead>

    <simpara>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either
    commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the copyright
    notices, and the license notice saying this License applies to the
    Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other
    conditions whatsoever to those of this License. You may not use technical
    measures to obstruct or control the reading or further copying of the
    copies you make or distribute. However, you may accept compensation in
    exchange for copies. If you distribute a large enough number of copies you
    must also follow the conditions in section 3.</simpara>

    <simpara>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above,
    and you may publicly display copies.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section3">3. COPYING IN
    QUANTITY</bridgehead>

    <simpara>If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly
    have printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the
    Document’s license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the
    copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts:
    Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back
    cover. Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify you as the
    publisher of these copies. The front cover must present the full title
    with all words of the title equally prominent and visible. You may add
    other material on the covers in addition. Copying with changes limited to
    the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the Document and satisfy
    these conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other
    respects.</simpara>

    <simpara>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit
    legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit reasonably)
    on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent pages.</simpara>

    <simpara>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document
    numbering more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable
    Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each
    Opaque copy a computer-network location from which the general
    network-using public has access to download using public-standard network
    protocols a complete Transparent copy of the Document, free of added
    material. If you use the latter option, you must take reasonably prudent
    steps, when you begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure
    that this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the stated
    location until at least one year after the last time you distribute an
    Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or retailers) of that edition
    to the public.</simpara>

    <simpara>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors
    of the Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to
    give them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the
    Document.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section4">4.
    MODIFICATIONS</bridgehead>

    <simpara>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document
    under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you release
    the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the Modified
    Version filling the role of the Document, thus licensing distribution and
    modification of the Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it. In
    addition, you must do these things in the Modified Version:</simpara>

    <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
      <listitem>
        <simpara>Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title
        distinct from that of the Document, and from those of previous
        versions (which should, if there were any, be listed in the History
        section of the Document). You may use the same title as a previous
        version if the original publisher of that version gives
        permission.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or
        entities responsible for authorship of the modifications in the
        Modified Version, together with at least five of the principal authors
        of the Document (all of its principal authors, if it has fewer than
        five), unless they release you from this requirement.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the
        Modified Version, as the publisher.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications
        adjacent to the other copyright notices.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license
        notice giving the public permission to use the Modified Version under
        the terms of this License, in the form shown in the Addendum
        below.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant
        Sections and required Cover Texts given in the Document’s license
        notice.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Include an unaltered copy of this License.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve the section Entitled “History”, Preserve its Title,
        and add to it an item stating at least the title, year, new authors,
        and publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title Page. If
        there is no section Entitled “History” in the Document, create one
        stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as
        given on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified
        Version as stated in the previous sentence.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document
        for public access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise
        the network locations given in the Document for previous versions it
        was based on. These may be placed in the “History” section. You may
        omit a network location for a work that was published at least four
        years before the Document itself, or if the original publisher of the
        version it refers to gives permission.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>For any section Entitled “Acknowledgements” or “Dedications”,
        Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve in the section all the
        substance and tone of each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or
        dedications given therein.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document,
        unaltered in their text and in their titles. Section numbers or the
        equivalent are not considered part of the section titles.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Delete any section Entitled “Endorsements”. Such a section
        may not be included in the Modified Version.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled
        “Endorsements” or to conflict in title with any Invariant
        Section.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.</simpara>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <simpara>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or
    appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material
    copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or all of
    these sections as invariant. To do this, add their titles to the list of
    Invariant Sections in the Modified Version’s license notice. These titles
    must be distinct from any other section titles.</simpara>

    <simpara>You may add a section Entitled “Endorsements”, provided it
    contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various
    parties — for example, statements of peer review or that the text has been
    approved by an organization as the authoritative definition of a
    standard.</simpara>

    <simpara>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text,
    and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the
    list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one passage of
    Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through
    arrangements made by) any one entity. If the Document already includes a
    cover text for the same cover, previously added by you or by arrangement
    made by the same entity you are acting on behalf of, you may not add
    another; but you may replace the old one, on explicit permission from the
    previous publisher that added the old one.</simpara>

    <simpara>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this
    License give permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert
    or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section5">5. COMBINING
    DOCUMENTS</bridgehead>

    <simpara>You may combine the Document with other documents released under
    this License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified
    versions, provided that you include in the combination all of the
    Invariant Sections of all of the original documents, unmodified, and list
    them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in its license
    notice, and that you preserve all their Warranty Disclaimers.</simpara>

    <simpara>The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and
    multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single copy.
    If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different
    contents, make the title of each such section unique by adding at the end
    of it, in parentheses, the name of the original author or publisher of
    that section if known, or else a unique number. Make the same adjustment
    to the section titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license
    notice of the combined work.</simpara>

    <simpara>In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled
    “History” in the various original documents, forming one section Entitled
    “History”; likewise combine any sections Entitled “Acknowledgements”, and
    any sections Entitled “Dedications”. You must delete all sections Entitled
    “Endorsements”.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section6">6. COLLECTIONS OF
    DOCUMENTS</bridgehead>

    <simpara>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other
    documents released under this License, and replace the individual copies
    of this License in the various documents with a single copy that is
    included in the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this
    License for verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other
    respects.</simpara>

    <simpara>You may extract a single document from such a collection, and
    distribute it individually under this License, provided you insert a copy
    of this License into the extracted document, and follow this License in
    all other respects regarding verbatim copying of that document.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section7">7. AGGREGATION WITH
    INDEPENDENT WORKS</bridgehead>

    <simpara>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other
    separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a
    storage or distribution medium, is called an “aggregate” if the copyright
    resulting from the compilation is not used to limit the legal rights of
    the compilation’s users beyond what the individual works permit. When the
    Document is included in an aggregate, this License does not apply to the
    other works in the aggregate which are not themselves derivative works of
    the Document.</simpara>

    <simpara>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these
    copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of the
    entire aggregate, the Document’s Cover Texts may be placed on covers that
    bracket the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic equivalent of
    covers if the Document is in electronic form. Otherwise they must appear
    on printed covers that bracket the whole aggregate.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section8">8. TRANSLATION</bridgehead>

    <simpara>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
    distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 4.
    Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special permission
    from their copyright holders, but you may include translations of some or
    all Invariant Sections in addition to the original versions of these
    Invariant Sections. You may include a translation of this License, and all
    the license notices in the Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers,
    provided that you also include the original English version of this
    License and the original versions of those notices and disclaimers. In
    case of a disagreement between the translation and the original version of
    this License or a notice or disclaimer, the original version will
    prevail.</simpara>

    <simpara>If a section in the Document is Entitled “Acknowledgements”,
    “Dedications”, or “History”, the requirement (section 4) to Preserve its
    Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual
    title.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section9">9. TERMINATION</bridgehead>

    <simpara>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document
    except as expressly provided under this License. Any attempt otherwise to
    copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute it is void, and will automatically
    terminate your rights under this License.</simpara>

    <simpara>However, if you cease all violation of this License, then your
    license from a particular copyright holder is reinstated (a)
    provisionally, unless and until the copyright holder explicitly and
    finally terminates your license, and (b) permanently, if the copyright
    holder fails to notify you of the violation by some reasonable means prior
    to 60 days after the cessation.</simpara>

    <simpara>Moreover, your license from a particular copyright holder is
    reinstated permanently if the copyright holder notifies you of the
    violation by some reasonable means, this is the first time you have
    received notice of violation of this License (for any work) from that
    copyright holder, and you cure the violation prior to 30 days after your
    receipt of the notice.</simpara>

    <simpara>Termination of your rights under this section does not terminate
    the licenses of parties who have received copies or rights from you under
    this License. If your rights have been terminated and not permanently
    reinstated, receipt of a copy of some or all of the same material does not
    give you any rights to use it.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section10">10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF
    THIS LICENSE</bridgehead>

    <simpara>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of
    the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions
    will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in detail
    to address new problems or concerns. See <link
    xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Copyleft</link>.</simpara>

    <simpara>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version
    number. If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of
    this License “or any later version” applies to it, you have the option of
    following the terms and conditions either of that specified version or of
    any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the Free
    Software Foundation. If the Document does not specify a version number of
    this License, you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft)
    by the Free Software Foundation. If the Document specifies that a proxy
    can decide which future versions of this License can be used, that proxy’s
    public statement of acceptance of a version permanently authorizes you to
    choose that version for the Document.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section11">11.
    RELICENSING</bridgehead>

    <simpara>“Massive Multiauthor Collaboration Site” (or “MMC Site”) means
    any World Wide Web server that publishes copyrightable works and also
    provides prominent facilities for anybody to edit those works. A public
    wiki that anybody can edit is an example of such a server. A “Massive
    Multiauthor Collaboration” (or “MMC”) contained in the site means any set
    of copyrightable works thus published on the MMC site.</simpara>

    <simpara>“CC-BY-SA” means the Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0
    license published by Creative Commons Corporation, a not-for-profit
    corporation with a principal place of business in San Francisco,
    California, as well as future copyleft versions of that license published
    by that same organization.</simpara>

    <simpara>“Incorporate” means to publish or republish a Document, in whole
    or in part, as part of another Document.</simpara>

    <simpara>An MMC is “eligible for relicensing” if it is licensed under this
    License, and if all works that were first published under this License
    somewhere other than this MMC, and subsequently incorporated in whole or
    in part into the MMC, (1) had no cover texts or invariant sections, and
    (2) were thus incorporated prior to November 1, 2008.</simpara>

    <simpara>The operator of an MMC Site may republish an MMC contained in the
    site under CC-BY-SA on the same site at any time before August 1, 2009,
    provided the MMC is eligible for relicensing.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="addendum">ADDENDUM: How to use this
    License for your documents</bridgehead>

    <simpara>To use this License in a document you have written, include a
    copy of the License in the document and put the following copyright and
    license notices just after the title page:</simpara>

    <screen>Copyright © YEAR YOUR NAME

            Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the
            terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or any later version
            published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no
            Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in
            the section entitled “GNU Free Documentation License”.</screen>

    <simpara>If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover
    Texts, replace the “with… Texts.” line with this:</simpara>

    <screen>with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the Front-Cover Texts
            being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST.</screen>

    <simpara>If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other
    combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the
    situation.</simpara>

    <simpara>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we
    recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free
    software license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit their
    use in free software.</simpara>
  </appendix>
</book>
